<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discours hapned. Betwene an hermite called Nicephorus &amp; a yong louer called Tristan, who for that his Mistresse Petronilla entred into religion would faine become an hermite. All faithfullie dravven out of the historie of Petronilla, composed in French by the Right Reuerend Father in God Iohn Peter Camus Bishop of Belley. And translated into English by P.S.P.</title>
            <title>Petronille. English</title>
            <author>Camus, Jean-Pierre, 1584-1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 189 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 92 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B11947</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4551</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116152</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851369</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851369</idno>
            <idno type="VID">178129</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B11947)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178129)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1404:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discours hapned. Betwene an hermite called Nicephorus &amp; a yong louer called Tristan, who for that his Mistresse Petronilla entred into religion would faine become an hermite. All faithfullie dravven out of the historie of Petronilla, composed in French by the Right Reuerend Father in God Iohn Peter Camus Bishop of Belley. And translated into English by P.S.P.</title>
                  <title>Petronille. English</title>
                  <author>Camus, Jean-Pierre, 1584-1652.</author>
                  <author>P. S. P., fl. 1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 171, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. Blageart],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Paris :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed with permission 1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; some pages misbound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Clergy --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:178129:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOVRS HAPNED.</p>
            <p>BETWENE AN HERMITE called Nicephorus &amp; a yong louer called Triſtan, who for that his Miſtreſſe Petronilla entred into Religion would faine become an Hermite.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All faithfullie dravven out of the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie of Petronilla, compoſed in French by the Right Reuerend Father in God</hi> IOHN PETER CAMVS <hi>Bishop of Belley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Tranſlated into English by P. S. P.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed with Permiſſion.</p>
            <p>1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:178129:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Academioe Gantabrigienſis Liber</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:178129:2"/>
            <head>TO THE CATHOLIKES of Irland.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>ENOWNED Catholikes the Hiſtoire of Petro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nilla Coming to my hands, compoſed by the Right Reuerend Father in God Iohn Peter Camus Bishop of Belley a man of Knovvne learning, emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <note place="margin">He vvra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te many bookes.</note> pietie &amp; of an Apoſtolicall life, the fancie tooke me to imploy ſome time in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it, not doubting but coming from ſo famous an Authour, I should find ſome thing in it worth my labour. Going then forward in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:178129:3"/> therof, amongſt many other good things, I lighted vpon this Treatiſe, which when I conſidered, I ſaid thus to my ſelf: it might be thought, that this man had reuelation, or ſome notice giuen him of the emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; varia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which is betweene the Hierarchicall Clergie and the Regulars in Irland, &amp; that in conſequens therof he framed this Diſcours. For it is ſaid, that the Regulars there, thinking therby to magnifie and extoll themſelues (for I know no other reaſon they can haue for it) make no conſcience nor ſcrupule both in their publike ſermons, and in their priuat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſations amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt you, to ſay and affirme, that Prieſts are but meere Seculars,
<pb facs="tcp:178129:3"/> that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues are true Paſtours, that it belongs to them only to be called Fathers, that they are the choice and beſt part of the Eccleſiaſticall Hierarchie, &amp; which is more abſurd, that their Regular Superiours are more worthy then Bishops. All which aſſertions manifeſtly falſe, and ill becoming men whoſe inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is chiefely grounded in humilitie and contempt of worldly honour and reſpects, being touched and diſcuſſed in this Treatiſe, I thought in my loue and naturall affection towards you, my deere Country men, that I was in a manner bound, fearing theſe things should giue you ſome erronious impreſſions, to impart it vnto
<pb facs="tcp:178129:4"/> you. Wherupon I tooke the paines to tranſlate it out of French into English &amp; to haue it printed. And if I shall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that it takes effect, &amp; cauſe the Delinque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts reflect vpon their errour, herin &amp; vpon that ſaying of S. Iames the Apoſtle: <hi>If any man think himſelf to be Religious</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iac.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 26</note> 
               <hi>not bridling his tongue, but ſeducing his hart, this mans Religion is vaine,</hi> then will I think my labour well imployed. And that which is moſt to be deſired of them is, that they doe conſider firſt, that ſuch aſſertions and compariſons doe more hurt then good, do rather deſtroy then edifie, rather peruert then conuert the people from their euill courſes, &amp; rather breede hate &amp; enuie, then loue
<pb facs="tcp:178129:4"/> or charitie: and ſecondly that they conſider, that Prieſthood, which is the fontaine and fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all Eccleſiaſticàll fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, is the ſame in Secular Prieſts (as they terme them) and in Regulars, whence Prieſts may iuſtlie ſay to the Regulars with ſaint Paul, that if they be He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes ſo are they, if they be <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 22.</note> Iſraëlites ſoe are they, if they be the ſeede of Abraham ſo are they, if they be Miniſters of CHRIST ſo are they; yea more, that they are their elders and haue higher offices and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the Church then they haue. And for you worthy cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions I shall deſire you not to be ſcandalized to ſee one Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike write againſt an other,
<pb facs="tcp:178129:5"/> beleeuing that Catholikes as Catholikes doe agree in matters of Faith, but as men that they may varie in other opinions. S. Peter and S. Paul, S. Auſtin <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 15. <hi>Hieron. ep.</hi> 86. <hi>Aug. ep.</hi> 8 <hi>&amp; ſequ. Euſ. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 25 <hi>Bedal.</hi> 3. <hi>Hiſtor. Angl. cap.</hi> 24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 25. <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>Dan.</hi> 20.</note> and S. Hierome diſagreed in ſome opinions without breach of fayth or charitie. About the obſeruation of Eaſter there was great debate betwixt Saincts &amp; Saincts till the Church decided the controuerſie; yea Angels haue diſſented in opinions. But this you may note in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, that learned Doctours in theſe Countries, and ſome of them Religious men, with whom I did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fer of the ſame, do much admeere that the Regulars in Irland do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teſt with the Clergie for the ſaid points, wheras in no
<pb facs="tcp:178129:5"/> Catholike Countries do the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulars ſpeake of the like, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine themſelues within the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct of their Monaſteries, and the obſeruance of their Rules, which teach the quit contrarie of all that they doe in this kind And if they will alleage that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no Monaſteries in Irla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d they muſt goe vp &amp; downe amongſt you, like other Prieſts, me thinks they should the leſſe claime any perfection or reſpect ouer other Prieſts, and my warrant for this is S. Hierome, who ſpeaking of ſuch Monks and Religious men ſaith: <hi>Sicut piſcis extra aquam ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret vita ſic Monachus extra Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſterium.</hi> As fish being out of the water doth want life, ſo doth a Monke or Religious man
<pb facs="tcp:178129:6"/> being out of his Monaſterie. For the life of a Religious man, as ſuch, is to obſerue his Rules, and keepe his vowes, which he cannot doe ſo well, if he do it at all, being cóuerſant in the world, &amp; not doing it, what prerogatiue can he claime ouer others? To conclude if the Regulars be true Paſtours as is aboue ſaid, how can they excuſe themſelues that they take no more care of their flock then ſome odd times like paſſingers to preach vnto them, God knowes with litle fruict? Who will not ſay but the good Prieſt is more like to be the true Paſtour: <hi>Who giueth his life for his sheepe,</hi> ſeruing them, not by ſtarts but all the yeere long, by day and by night, in heate and in
<pb facs="tcp:178129:6"/> cold, in raine and in tempeſt, with much miſerie &amp; litle profit? Laſtly who can beleeue that the Regulars are true or proper Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours whenas they cannot take any ſuch chardge vpon them if firſt they be not diſpenſed with all in their vovves. Add that in Catholike Countries, where all Clergie men get their due, they cannot preach nor Miniſter any Sacrament out of their owne Conuents without the expreſſe leaue of the Bishop of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſe, and of the Paſtour of the place, conformable to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 24.</note> of Trent? Howſoeuer they will anſwere to all theſe things, I make no doubt but after their accuſtomed manner, ſome of them vvill ſay (for I Knovv that
<pb facs="tcp:178129:7"/> many good men amongſt them doe not approue ſuch things) that he is no frend of Religious men that doth propound them. But God is my vvitneſſe, I do honour &amp; reſpect all Religious men, and vvish all others to do the ſame, as long as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine themſelues vvithin the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of their Rules, &amp; that they do not prefer the honour of their order, as many ſeeme to doe, to the honour and ſeruice of God, to vvhoſe diuine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection I commit you, and pray him, to giue vs all the Spirit of vnion and charitie, &amp; ſo reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your deuoted ſeruant in CHRIST IESVS P. S. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:178129:7"/>
            <head>A DISCOVRS HAPNED.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Betvveene an Hermite called Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cephorus and a yong louer called Triſtan, who for that his Miſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe Petronilla entred into Religion vvould faine become an Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Mitting the hiſtorie of all that paſt betweene Triſtan and petronilla, and the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall end which came of their loue, I will only rehearſe the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours paſt betweene Triſtan &amp; Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus, contayning many points much diſputed of in theſe our dayes. Triſtan a proper and wel bredd yong gentilman much grieued that his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:178129:8"/> petronilla whom he purſued ſo long time (of diſpleaſure that shee could not obtaine her parents conſent to marrie him) went into Religion, reſolued alſo to retire himſelf from the world in ſome religious Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; but after communicating his reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution therin to ſeuerall Religious men of diuers orders and getting their opinions therof, at length he follovved his owne fancie &amp; inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which was to goe to the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe and leade an Heremiticall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe; and the Perinean mountaines vvhich ſeparate France from Spaigne being the neereſt vnto him, he went thither, taking with him a good purſe of mony and his lute, at which he was very skilfull. But neither his lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te nor his ſolitarineſſe did any thing aſſwage his paſſion, or make him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the creature which brought him to that anxietie of minde, but rather inflamed him more, eſpeciallie the lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te conformable to the old prouerb, which ſaith, that muſick is an impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunat
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:178129:8"/> geſt to a hart afflicted. Being then in this perplexitie he was told that not farr from him there was a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uote and wel built Hermitage wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in dwelt a venerable Hermite who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſainctitie of life gaue a good odou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to all the Country about, and who by long experience did learne how to guide himſelfe to perfection by the way of ſolitarineſſe in that wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. His good Angell made Triſtan draw towards this ſainctly old man, vvho receiued him with the ſame charitie wherwith he was accuſtomed to receiue and intertaine other paſſing Pilgrimes (for he was in pilgrimes weede) who ſtraying from their way in thoſe dreadfull deſerts, fell ſometi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes vpon the litle path which leade to his ſell. Triſtan beholding him did take him for an Angell of God, and beleeued that he was the Raphaël which would conduct him to Rages, I would ſay, to the perfection of the contemplatiue life. Hauing then brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie declared his intent to the good
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:178129:9"/> Hermite, he gaue him for anſweare, that to loue a thing it is neceſſarie to know it before, and that the Heremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall life as well as the Monaſticall doth require a good approbation of a man before he be admitted to it. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan hauing ſubmitted himſelfe to him in all things. My child, quoth father Nicephorus, for ſo they called this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious man, it is nothing for a man to vndertake ſuch a life if he be not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to it by God, &amp; amongſt many that are called, few are chooſen. I know wel that it doth not appertaine but to God, to know perfectlie and waigh iuſtlie the hearts of men, yet his will is that his ſeruants do ſee and trie whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be of true or falſe coine: the touchſtone of ſuch as are called to the ſeruice of God is, the renunciation of all things, and of themſelues alſo. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, quoth Triſtan, if that be the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of the elect I haue it; for I do free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie quitt the world, the ſubiect which retayned me in it being ſeparated from me, &amp; it will be eaſie likewiſe for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:178129:9"/> me to forſake my ſelfe ſeing I haue relinquished an obiect of which I did eſteeme much more then of my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>My child, quoth Nicephorus, the warrs ſeeme ſweet, according the prouerb, to ſuch as did not trie it, do not triumph before the victorie, and do not proclaime victorie before the battle; none shall be crowned, ſaith the word of veritie, that will not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonablie and valorouſlie fight, and the battle which wee haue with our ſelfe <note place="margin">Selfe loue ingrauen in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> loue doth laſt as long as our verie li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues: for that errour is ſo deepely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauen in our nature, as it doth ſubſiſt after wee renounce our ſelues; wee may mortifie it, but not make it die, contrary wiſe it ſeemes like the fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Gyant, to take new forces from it proſtration and ouerthrow, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke great trees, the more they be sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, the faſter the fix their rootes. It may be aſſaulted but rarely ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, &amp; neuer rooted out: the walls of that rebellious Hiëricho, although
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:178129:10"/> they be vndermined and ſometimes razed to the ground, yet do they get vp againe of themſelues. I do not ſay this to diſcourage you, nor to imitat thoſe timorous ſpies, which would fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne diſſwade the children of Iſraël from vndertaking the conqueſt of the land of promis; I know there be diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties in it, but I tell you with Ioſüe and Caleb, that you may boldlie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the power of our lord, who, if he be for you, nothing can preuaile againſt you, for who can reſiſt the will of the higheſt power, of this Lord of armies, who is terrible ouer all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, if he vndertake to fight with you? But you muſt not hope that he wil put himſelf of your ſide, if you do not put all your truſt and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in him, by a perfect diſtruſt of your ſelf, which may not conſiſt with thoſe loftie termes, which promis mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes, and carrying you vpon the wings of the wind make you aſpire to great matters, which ſurpaſſe the reach of a man that is not yet a Nouice. It is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:178129:10"/> not, that I do lightlie iudge of your ſoule, which I beleeue is more perfect then my owne, who ſerues God ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligently and loue him ſo coldlie, nor that I am ignorant but in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion of the Babylon of the world, God hath ſeruants and ſecret diſciples, which do not bow their knees to Baal, and that keepe their hearts pure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the impuritie of the world, of which number you may be; add that the extraordinarie effects of grace do produce in an inſtant admirable conuerſions, which puts thoſe that are replenished with it, in a ſtate of great perfection, conformable to that which is written, that the workes of God are perfect and without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that is to ſay, without defect.</p>
            <p>Triſtan, who beleeued that this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours of the Hermite did tend to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr and put of his reception, eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming (as he was full of worldly maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes) that the Hermite did feare that chardging himſelf with him, his almes would be too short to furnish him a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:178129:11"/> portion ſaid, Father the time will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke knowne whether I be touched with true or fained charitle, &amp; the triall will make manifeſt the force or the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my vocation. but to the end that you may not think that I come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to incommodat, or importune you, I will shew vnto you that it is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to occommodat you, &amp; to draw you from the paine of going here and there to ſearche your liuing, which muſt bring much interruption to your contemplation, which require repoſe &amp; ſilence, and may not be had but in the wilderneſſe. Know then that being left an orphan without father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I was emancipated by publick au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie a litle before the terme of my maioritie &amp; conſequently put in the poſſeſſion of my goods which are not ſo ſmall but they are ſufficient to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish twentie Hermits as you are, &amp; I beleeue that not making the vow of pouertie in any Religious order, that I may keepe them and diſpoſe of them as God shall inſpire me. We
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:178129:11"/> shall then liue together &amp; what reuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion wee shall haue we will beſtow it in almes, &amp; in ſuch other pious works as you shall think good, without trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling our ſelues to begg for our main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance. And to shew that it is true, that I came not hither with emptie hands, or vnfurnished of things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to nourishe and cloathe my ſelfe, behold a ſcantlet of the matter.</p>
            <p>Then did he shew the Hermite a great purſe full of piſtolls, and alſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me pretious ſtones more worth then gold, and yet did occupie leſſe place. Good Nicephorus, who did not ſee while he kept in this wilderneſſe ſuch great quantitie of this yealoue mettall, whoſe luſter doth dazle the eyes of many men in the world, did firmely beleeue in his minde that he was the Tentator, who vnder a humaine shape came to diuert him from the way of perfection, which is that of holy po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, which he traced for many yee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res within his litle caue. Wherupon ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming himſelfe with the marke of our
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:178129:12"/> ſaluation and vttering the name of our Sauiour with a low voice, ſeing that Triſtan did not vanish away, to cleare himſelfe of his doubt, he tooke him ſoftlie by the arme and ſaid to him; If I had not knowne that ſpirits haue nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fleshe nor bones, as I do feele you to haue, I would ſay that it is the Diuell that came to ſollicit me to my ruine, offring me richeſſe, as he did to the ſonne of God when he aſſaulted him in the wilderneſſe. But I feare that not taking vpon him the forme of man he doth poſſeſſe your hearr to produce in myne the ſame effect, &amp; to ſlide into it the death of grace by the venime of auarice. I will then ſay vnto you the ſame that the Apoſtle ſaid to Simon Magus, away with your gold &amp; ſiluer from me, which I know are the I dolls of the world, to which they are like, that do adore them, and that put their confidence in them: that man is abondantly riche that is poore in IESVS CHRIST. I loue my begging, by which I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quer heauen for my ſelfe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:178129:12"/> (&amp; make others to conquer it for them, making them to merit euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting goods when they giue me of their earthly goods) better then all your treaſure: It is long ſince I haue put of that shirt of earthly poſſeſſion, and how should I putt it on againe? I haue washed my feete &amp; chaſed from my minde thoſe groſe affections, and how should I contaminat them of the new? I will neuer call back againe what I haue once quitted and renounced with a good will for the loue of my Maiſter; he hath nourished me ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeeres in theſe deſerts, both with the dew of heauen, which is the Manna of his conſolations, and with the fatt of the earth, which is the daylie bread of the neceſſitie of the body, as I haue all ſubiect to bleſſe his prouidence, &amp; to confirme my ſelfe in this truth that ſuch as ſeeke for God and his kingdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me can neuer want any thing. For my part, I will promis you no gold nor ſiluer, but that only which God will ſend me by the hands of ſuch as he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:178129:13"/> shall inſpire to do me charitie, I will impart it to you. In the meane ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me I will tell you, that if you will do as Iacob did, quitt the houſe of the traitour Laban, which is the world, to inioye the embracing of Lia and Rachell, to witt, Action and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, it is neceſſarie that you burie thoſe Idolls at the foote of the Terebinthe of the croſſe, and that glorifying in nothing but in IESVS CHRIST crucified, you will imitat him in his nuditie, gloriouſly ignominious, by depriuing your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe of the care of temporall richeſſe, according the Counſell, which he gaue to that yong gentilman, who was like to you, to quitt all, that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 21.</note> he might be perfect, not admitting him of his traine if firſt he vvould not diſtribut to the poore all that he poſſeſſed. But my ſonne quoth the good Hermitte, I feare you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble too much this yong man, &amp; that like vnto him you will retire your ſelfe with à heauie heart, not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:178129:13"/> being able to digeſt the bitterneſſe of this drugg, which make men for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all the goods of the earthe, that they may aſpire to heauenly goods, and that you will not ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely diſpoſſeſſe your ſelfe of them as Iacob did putt of the skins which couered his hands, &amp; good Ioſeph his cloake.</p>
            <p>That I may not lie vnto you, quoth Triſtan, I could neuer beleeue that for being an Hermite a man muſt haue renounced the inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of his forefathers, but well I knew it to be neceſſarie for to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of thoſe religious orders, in which is made the ſolemne Vow of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie; a thing not only neceſſarie, but alſo very eaſie in thoſe great Communalties whether they be ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che <note place="margin">The vovv of pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie very eaſie in Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties.</note> or begging Communalties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Religion doth oblige it ſelfe to intertaine the Religious as they do conſecrat themſelues to the obſeruance of the rules of the Religion. But an Hermitte that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:178129:14"/> alone without ſupport is often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times truſting to a badd dynner while he exſpects Manna or larks to fall from heauen to him; as they did to the Iſraëlites; for God doth not shew ſuch fauours to all nations nor worke ſuch miracles vpon all occaſions. Such as putt their truſt in God, quoth the Hermite, are not shaked no more then is Mount Sion: He that dwells in Hieruſalem, which is in the protection of the God of heauen, &amp; whoſe very gates he doth loue, is no more moued when he is in want, then when he hath plentie of all things, being aſſured that the hand of God is not shortned, nor his power diminished. He that hath care of the croes litle ones being abandonned by their Dames, and of the leaſt ſparrow; yea, of the leaſt flie, will neuer abandon him that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues iuſt before him all his life time. The ſunne will ſooner faile to lighten the world, then his prouidence to shine vpon ſuch as he loues; he that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:178129:14"/> ſpreds his beames and pouers his rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne equally vpon the iuſt and the vniuſt, that giues nourishment to all flesh, and that neede do no more but open his hand to replenish all creatures with benediction.</p>
            <p>All that may be good, quoth Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan, in the pulpet but the practiſe is quitt otherwiſe. For my part, I would make no difficultie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce to the inheritance of my forefathers, nor to make a vow of pouertie in a good Conuent, which should be well rented, or being of a begging order, that should be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated in a good cittie, where they eate the ſinnes of the people, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re all men labour for you while you pray for all men, where they find the bread ready baked, the wine all pure, the meat ready dreſſed, where they haue no care of any thing, nor think of tomorrow, practiſing, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie &amp; in good earneſt theſe words of the Scripture: <hi>Aske and thou shalt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>haue, ſeeke and thou shalt find;</hi> But
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:178129:15"/> without, that, to renounce my owne, it is a thing that all the eloquence of men and of the Angels may not perſwade me to do, for I do ſee but too much euery day how ſottish and ridiculous it is, to be a poore prieſt.</p>
            <p>So it is without doubt according <note place="margin">It is a glorious thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God to be a poore prieſt.</note> the world, ſaid the Hermite, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God it is a glorious thing, yea, before that great God, who makes but follie of the wiſdome of the world, &amp; of the follie of the croſſe wiſdome, and who doth confound the faſt and pompe of richeſſe by humble po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, before him that came to euangelize the poore, who doth heare their prayers, who calls him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf their father and tutour, who doth extoll them in his iudgment as much as they are vilipended and held ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect in the iudgments of worldlings. But thoſe that are inſtructed in the schoole of the croſſe, which is fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to the Gentils, and ſcandall to the Iewes, but the vertue and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pience of God to the faithfull are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:178129:15"/> of an other beliefe, they hold the poore to be very happie, according the ſentence pronounced by the proper mouth of the ſonne of God: but the children of the word do not vnderſtand that probleme of ſtrong Samſon, becauſe they do not glorie but in the multitude of their richeſſe. I muſt for all that graunt vnto you, <note place="margin">Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eaſie.</note> that the pouertie of Monaſticall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons hath this aduantage of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie of Hermites and ſecular prieſts (as they call them) that it is well shrouded from all preſſing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities within a well gouerned co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaltie. You know I ſpeake of beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging orders, for to ſpeake of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentuall friars which liue by their reuenewes, they are not poore but in particular, in common they are riche, and they are poore inough in as much as they haue no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie of any thing; in this fashion then may they be ſaid to be poore in the middeſt of their richeſſe, and riche in the middeſt of their pouertie.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:178129:16"/> But the others albeit they be poore not only in particular but alſo in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, yet their pouertie is alwaies ſupported, ſuccoured and applauded, or at leaſtwiſe honored and eſteemed, in ſort that their ſufferances are regarded, and their wants glorious; they are riche in honnour, yea, in the middeſt of their ſufferances. In ſteade that a poore Hermite is deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed by euery body, his complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes are reiected, his wants vnknowne, his neceſſities do not appeere to any but to God: He is all alone, he is fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, and abandoned, hauing no body to comfort him, nor to take co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of his miſeries, none to caſt him into the pond wherin he might fish ſome reliefe.</p>
            <p>The ſame, I ſay of a prieſt that is in neceſſitie, euery body doth laugh at him, and in ſteade of ſuccouring him they vpbraid and floud him, they chardge him with falſe reprocheſſe and calumnies, ſo that he may well ſay with the Pſalmiſt: O lord the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procheſſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:178129:16"/> of thoſe that Diſdayne your deare Vertue of pouertie, with which you haue beene borne, you liued and died, making your ſelf nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and poore to replenish vs with the ineſtimable richeſſe and treaſures of your merits; theſe reprocheſſe ô Lord are fallen vpon me, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion hath couered my face: <hi>I am</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.</note> 
               <hi>made a ſtranger to my ovvne brothers;</hi> and a vacabond to the children of my owne mother.</p>
            <p>Father, quoth Triſtan, that is the thing which I find leaſt ſupportable of the infinit euells, which acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie pouertie: for honour of all the goods which doth inuiro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs being moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, I would ſooner ſuffer that they should touch the ball of myne eye, then ingage me in that point. And. I do graunt vnto you that I am not yet come to that point of mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that I may ſuffer and indure ieſts and contumelies no more then did the Prophet Eliſeus, much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re holy and more patient then I am,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:178129:17"/> that could not indure the litle chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to reproach vnto him that he was bald, an imperfection very light and naturall. and which as it should ſeeme he should acknowledg, and mocke the weakneſſe of thoſe litle ſoules, rather then deſtroie them by the imprecation and curſes wihich he fulminated againſt them.</p>
            <p>My ſonne, quoth Nicephorus, you take this example by a bad bias, &amp; handle the brone where it burnes. The Prophet did not regard the ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trage which thoſe children did vnto him, as an iniurie done to his owne perſonne, he was too humble to take it in that ſort: but he did it to magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his office, for he would be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of men as the Miniſter of God, and the diſpencer of his Myſteries; and becauſe he carried the ambaſſade of God, and that an affront or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace done to an Ambaſſadour doth hurt the honour of his Maiſter, and returne to the preiudice of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie that ſent him, according that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:178129:17"/> which is written: <hi>He that heares you heares me, and he that deſpiſeth you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiſeth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luca</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>me.</hi> For this reaſon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet prayed God that he would cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe thoſe inſolent boyes with exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar punishment, to teach great men what the fire of Gods choler would do being once kindled in drie wood, if it did conſume the greene wood with ſo great ardour; and what do you know but the corporall euell which he procured to them boyes was cauſe of their ſpirituall good, and of the Saluation of their ſoules, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them to taſt of death in an age more capable of innocencie then of malice, and conſequentlie more ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible of Gods grace then of his wrathe? in ſtead that had they in an age more reepe filled vp the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their ſinnes, and gone forward in their vice, they might perchance acquire their damnation. In this ſort did S. Paule deliuer to Sathan the body of that fornicatour, who made the liuing temple of God the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:178129:18"/> of a lecher to ſaue his ſoule from euerlaſting damnation. O my child how yong thou art yet in the warfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of the croſſe, which in it ſelf is no more dolorous then ignominious &amp; shamefull, yea, execrable, according that ſaying: <hi>Curſed is euery one that ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on a tree.</hi> How farr you ſtraie from the ſtandard of him who for vs was <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.</note> loaden with reprocheſſe, who did not turne his face from thoſe that ſpett vpon it, nor his cheekes from thoſe that did buffet them, nor his chinne-from thoſe that pulled of his beard; how farr, I ſay, you goe from him who was made a ſpectacle before his eternall father, before the Angels and before men, who was expoſed to be a mocking ſtock to thoſe that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we him nayled vpon the croſſe, to be ieſted by them &amp; to nodd and shake their heads on him? How badd a diſciple wouldeſt thou be to thoſe great Apoſtles, thoſe high montaignes whereon is laid the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the cittie of God, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:178129:18"/> frolike and ioyfull from the great aſſemblies where they were flouted and contumeliouſly handled; for the publicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſacred name and holy doctrine of IESVS CHRIST? Verely you muſt cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge your ſtile and language, and alſo your thoughts and maximes, if you perſeuere in that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire of a religious life, eſpeciallie that which regard the mortification of honour: for as I haue alreadie told you, the Conuentuall pouertie is reſpected and reuerenced, but our pouertie is mocked and flouted.</p>
            <p>So I beleeue, quoth Triſtan, that you Hermites are not poore but of neceſſitie; and not of free will, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of which your pouertie may not haue the glorie of the voluntarie which the Euangelicall pouertie doth deſerue. This is the cauſe why men putt you not in the ranke of regular but of ſecular beggers, who are redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to neceſſitie by the deſaſter of fortune, which if they ſupport with patience, I beleeue they shall haue
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:178129:19"/> honour befote God who ſees their hearts, but not before men. And that I do not lye vnto you, I would not eſteeme it an act of prudence of him that hath à patrimonie and makes himſelf an Hermite, to renounce to that which he doth poſſeſſe, to make himſelf afterwards by begging odious and importune to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, perſwading my ſelf that a man should drinck of the water of his owne ceſterne, and draw the laſt drop of it, before he would goe to the well or fontaine of his neighbour, being that it is reaſonable that euery man liue of the goods which God gaue him, or at leaſtwiſe, that he eate his bread by the ſweat of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes.</p>
            <p>Deare ſir, quoth the Hermite, the holy Apoſtle doth ſay, that being a litle one he ſpoake according his age but comming to be more great, he had thoughts and diſcourſes of a hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gher kind. I know well by your ſong that you are yet in a ſpirituall infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:178129:23"/> but when you shall be more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced in it, you will change thoſe humaine maximes into Euangelicall axiomes, which are of a higher note, and of a more excellent accent; if thou haddeſt beene a Religious man thou wouldeſt learne to ſpeake ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording the precepts of Religion, which conſiſt in the practiſe of the Euangelicall counſells.</p>
            <p>That is good, quoth Triſtan, for thoſe Religious men which oblige themſelues by vowes, but not for you Hermites, who do nothing but what you pleaſe, who liue after your owne fancie, and who are your owne maiſters. I will replie vnto you, quoth the Hermite, that which an ancient painture ſaid to a great lord, who <note place="margin">The ſaying of an ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t painteur.</note> tooke vpon himſelf within his shopp to diſcours of the art of painting, as many words as you ſpeake are ſo many ſoleciſmes againſt my art, hold your peace or els my apprentices will mock your ignorance. It is true that your ignorance is pardonable,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:178129:24"/> conſidering that being a ſoildiour (for Triſtan had a ſwerd at his ſide) you ſpeake of Religious affaires, euen as a Churchman would ſpeake of matters of warrs. But if thou wilt inrolle thy ſelf in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſpirituall warfare of Religion you will diſcours more netely and more correctly of theſe things. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, quoth Triſtan, I told you alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy that I deſire much to be an Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite, but not a Religious man. And I, quoth Nicephorus, do anſwere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that that is as if you would ſay, I would faine be a reaſonable creature but not a man, or otherwiſe, I would faine be a Monke and no Religious man; or thus, I would be a Religious man and no Monke, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that a Monke &amp; a Religious <note place="margin">A Monke &amp; a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious man is the ſame thing.</note> man is the ſame thing, as is a man and a reaſonable creature. But many, ſaith Triſtan, do not vnderſtand it ſo, for I haue ſeene many Religious men which would take it for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie, &amp; for a kind of diſgrace to be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:178129:24"/> called Monks, and ſuch as confeſſe themſelues to be Monks and are ſo named in their rules are glad to be called Religious men, ſo much this holy mame of Monke, ſo venerable <note place="margin">The name Monke novv out of requeſt</note> in ancient time is become diſagrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the eares of this our age, and that without doubt, through the fault of thoſe that did profane and disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour it by their badd liues.</p>
            <p>You ſay true, quoth the Hermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, and this imaginarie diſtinction hath beene inuented of late yeeres, and that only in France, becauſe of the hereſie which defamed that holy name of Monke, as she did open her vnpure mouthe againſt the church, corrupting that which shee knew, and blaſpeming that which shee knew not, or was ignorant of, and lancing out quippes &amp; tants (in which she putts all the force of her argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) againſt the moſt ſacred my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of our holy faith. And when I ſay that this diſtinction of a Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke and a Religious man is of a new
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:178129:25"/> impreſſion, and came lately out of the braines of ſome which ground themſelues vpon imaginations diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. I know not how, I do not ſay it of any contempt of their ſubtilitie, but to maintaine the truthe, of which I haue for witneſſes all thoſe that are beyond the Alps &amp; the Perinean montaignes, as the Italians and Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, <note place="margin">The vvord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious is not vſed in Spaine nor in Iralie.</note> among which the word Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious is not knowne, albeit thoſe Countries do abound more with Monks, then doth our Countrie of France. The Italians do call Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men 1. <hi>Monachi,</hi> or 1. <hi>Fratti,</hi> the Spaniards call then <hi>Los Monyes, or los Frayles,</hi> which is as much to ſay, as the Monks or Friars of ſuch an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. As for the name Father, which the vulgar ſort do giue to the Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, who are honored with the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotall character, and with the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnitie of prieſthood, it was not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed in the begining of Monaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call inſtitution but to the Superiours of euery Monaſterie, who as ſuch, we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:178129:25"/> called Abbotts, which is as much to ſay as father, and all the reſt that were their children and ſubiects were called brothers. And to ſpeake as I think, if thoſe that are married folke haue not the qualitie or title of Fathers and mothers but when they haue iſſue, and that the heauens do fauour, them with the benediction to haue children; ſo this appellation of ſpirituall Fathers doth <note place="margin">Paſtours only are to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> not ſeeme to appertaine but to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours only, be they Prelats or infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour prieſts, who haue chardge of ſoules, and watch ouer them, as being bound to render an account of them to God. who is the Prince of Paſtours, the Bishop of our ſoules, and the grand Maiſter of the vinuerſall flock of the world. Which appellation of Father, if it be appropriated to ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple prieſts, principallie in the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Sacraments, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that in the diſpenſation of the Diuine myſteries they hold the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of the Paſtours, who can not do
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:178129:26"/> all things by their owne proper ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds and in proper perſon; and to ſpeake with the Canons, who do adminiſter the Sacraments by the allowance and permiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the proper Paſtour, leauing to our Doctours to decide who that is properlie ſpeaking, for there is a controuerſie of it, which should not be decided by a poore Hermite as I am. Neuertheleſſe ſuch as I am, in my youth, I made ſome voyages, and principallie into Italie, and made ſome ſtaye &amp; ſeiour in the Court of Rome, following a great Cardinal, I ſay great in ranke, as they are all, and greater in bloud and ſanctitie, as they are not all. You know the eminencie of the qualitie which thoſe famous Seigneurs haue, and to which the ſea Apoſtolick hath raiſed them: Yet when the Popes do draw them out of Cloiſters, taking their lamps from vnder the bushell, and putting it vpon the candleſtick, to the end that the light of their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits do lighten all the houſe of God,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:178129:26"/> which is the church, they neuer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the qualitie of brothers, or Friars, as the marke of their regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, no more then they forſake the colour of the habit of the order wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they made their profeſſion. Their titles are moſt renowned lord and right reuerend father in God, if he be a Bishop, brother ſuch a one, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal of the holy church of Rome, Bishop of ſuch a place, or prieſt or Deacon of ſuch a title.</p>
            <p>As for Bishops, when out of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Orders they are aſſumpted to Epiſcopall dignities, for a marke of their ancient regularitie, from the obſeruance of which they are exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted paſſing to an other obedience &amp; diſcipline, they carrie alwaies the colour, and in ſome ſort, the forme of their habit, albeit they paſſe from the ſtate of perfection to be acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to the ſtate of perfection acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <note place="margin">Bishops the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours of the Apoſt.</note> as the ſucceſſours of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, yet be it of humilitie, or of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to their oder, to the title of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:178129:27"/> Right Reuerend father in God, they add that of brother or Friar ſuch a Bishop, of ſuch a church: in which is ſeene that they take the name Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as they are Paſtours, and the name brother as they are Monks or Friars. Whence it may be concluded that the name Father doth not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly <note place="margin">Of vvhat should Friars be called fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> belong to Friars or Monks as ſuch, but to Paſtours and Prieſts who haue Chardg of ſoules. Add that the vulgar ſort ſpeaking of a Bishop that hath beene a Religious man do ſay; that Bishop is a Friar or Monke, and thoſe Prelats do not take it to ſcorne to be called Monks or Friars, as do in thoſe parts ſome ſimple Conuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Friars, otherwiſe called Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe vnto you, quoth Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan, that I haue as litle skill in tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe Monaſticall matters, as I haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in that kind of life, which is ſequeſtred from the world; Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I went ſtill with the common opinion, which as I perceiue is a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:178129:19"/> errour. Yet cannot I well yeld or aſſent to what you propoſe, when I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider that this word Monke doth ſignifie a man who of deuotion doth leade a ſolitarie life, which Conuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall friars do not, liuing in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie, and if I may ſo terme it, in troups within their Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uents, hauing all their exerciſes in common, &amp; being almoſt ſtill together, be it in the quire, or in the Refectorie, at their Chapter, or at their corporall labours, at their leſſons and at their conferences, and alſo at their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſations with the neighbours, in ſort that me thinks they haue reaſon to call themſelues Religious men, as it were men tyed together by a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie <note place="margin">Reaſon vvhy they may be called Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dravven out of the frenche vvord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lié.</note> of an vniforme life, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, that albeit their companies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of diuers members, they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe conducted by one &amp; the ſame ſpirit and mind, which is the plaſter and mortar by which they are tyed and ioyned in God the one to the other, according to that which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:178129:20"/> is written of the firſt Chriſtians, that they had not amongſt, them but one hart and one ſoule. And the moſt preſſing knots which bind them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, beſids the knot of charitie, which bind the moſt perfect of them, and is the great tye of perfection, are the ſolemne vowes, by which thoſe that be profeſt do oblige themſelues to the order in which they are incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated, &amp; the order in like manner doth oblige it ſelf to ſuch as it recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth. And the are thoſe vowes, as farr as I could learne of learned &amp; deuote Religious men, that put them <note place="margin">Their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne vovves putts the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</note> in the ſtate of perfection: in which are not the Anacorits who make not theſe vowes; at leaſtwiſe ſolemne, but lead a priuat and particular life, without hauing any other ſocietie with their neighbours, but that which tye all Chriſtians one to an other, as children of the ſame church.</p>
            <p>In the time of our Sauiour, ſaith the Hermite, Martha murmured againſt Marie. I ſee well that you haue
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:178129:20"/> learned all thoſe things out of the mouth of ſome Conuentuall friar animated by a kind of zeale, which if it be not indiſcrite and without ſcience, at leaſtwiſe, it is sharp, and bitter againſt vs poore Monks, the outcaſt and ſweeping of the world, and who are nothing els but voices, which by their grones and ſighes do make the Ecchos of theſe deſerts ring and ſound. But bleſſed by God, who in this qualitie made vs, at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe imitatours and followers of that great fore-runner of the Meſſias de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to haue beene the greateſt amongſt the children of men by the proper mouth of the ſonne of God, &amp; placed vs vpon Maries portion, which he ſaid to be the beſt, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the complaints and going about of Martha. There is <note place="margin">Friars approue nothing but their ovvne actions.</note> nothing more iniuſt then thoſe kind of people which approue nothing but their owne actions, and find nothing good but what they do themſelues. Happie is he that can eſcape their
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:178129:21"/> cenſures. In the meane time there is no charitie in theſe reprehenſions, for that vertue is not iealous, and in tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe kind of people nothing is ſeene but emulation, not of the beſt grace, as the Apoſtle ſaith, but ſuch as tend to certaine particularities, which breede partialities and theſe partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities ingendreth falſe imaginations of deuotion, which hath but the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke and not the true pith of pietie: for true pietie is good for all things, and all theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentions are good for nothing. Charitie doth no idle nor euell thing, and the effects which are ingendred of thoſe ſubtile que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, of thoſe ſtates of perfection, of theſe compariſons of liues, and of <note place="margin">Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons of liues &amp; orders are good for nothing.</note> the diuerſities of rules and Orders, are good for nothing, but very hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſome times to the reputation of many. Charitie is not puffe vp with pride, nor ambition, but humble and reſpectiue of all men, neuer prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring herſelfe to any. The hart which she doth poſſeſſe is neuer puffed vp
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:178129:21"/> with preſumption, neuer lifts vp it browes with ſcorne of any body, nor make it aſpire to great things; albeit shee be herſelfe very perfect, yet doth she apprehend this great word of perfection. She neuer ſeekes her owne proper intreſt nor profit, but that of IESVS CHRIST, &amp; in him that of the neighbour. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it is a diſeaſe common in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough within Cloiſters, and I dare ſay, in a manner contagious (not to deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe thoſe of other orders; for that had beene manifeſt follie) but ſo to eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of the order wherin they are the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues inrolled, as if there were none but it worthy of conſideration in the church of God. It is a Phariſaicall ſpeech to ſay, I am not like other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eſpecially like this Publican. I do not ſay but a Monke or Friar may, yea ought, as he is tyed in body &amp; habit to his Order, ſo ought he to haue a particular inclination to it, &amp; to loue it with a loue of preference, and ſingular prefere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: But this eſteeme
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:178129:22"/> should remaine with in his owne breaſt, without ſuffring it to paſſe out of his mouthe, in ſort that the account which he makes of it may not obfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcat the merits of other Regular co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies. For euen as all particular men, ſo all ſocieties haue receiued of God diuers graces and fauours, ſome this way, &amp; ſome that way, as they receiued ſo many liniaments of their viſages, as do diſtinguith them one from an other, and ſo many allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to call them from the world that would giue themſelues to pietie with more perfection. But, that they should thinke to exclude, either from the ſtate of perfection, or from pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to perfection (which is moſt deſirable) ſuch as do not make profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of that kind of Conuentuall and Monaſticall life, it would not be only to offend our faith, but alſo to ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue from the common opinion, and fall into abſurdities which may not be admitted by any of ſolide iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For if the ſtate of perfection
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:178129:22"/> by tyed to certaine obſeruations without which men may not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; or depend of an habit made after a certaine fashion, and of vowes, yea ſolemne, more then of the practiſe of thoſe heroicall vertues, which are counſelled in the Ghoſpell, who doth not ſee that it muſt be concluded that our Sauiour himſelf, the patter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne <note place="margin">Our Sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iour did not make the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vves of Religion.</note> of the mountaine, and not the modell only of perfection, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection it ſelfe, hath not beene in this ſtate, conſidering that we do not read that euer he made thoſe vowes in which they put the eſſence of the ſtate of perfection? The ſame may be ſaid of his holy mother, who by the imitation of her ſonne hauing perfectly obſerued obedience, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie and chaſtitie, ought neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to be held very perfect, albeit wee do not reade in expreſſe termes, that by vowes ſolemnely made, she pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to practiſe theſe Counſells. But if the church doth piouſly belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue with S. Hieroſme, that by theſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:178129:23"/> words, which she ſaid to the Angell who ſaluted her, how shall that be which thou ſaieſt, that I shall be a mother whenas, I know no man? Shee doth witneſſe that shee reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in her heart to keepe her inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie, and promiſed to God perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall virginitie; it is certaine that this interpretation is not yet propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the faithfull, as an article of faith, no more then is to this preſent her immaculate Conception, but well is propoſed, that shee was a Virgin before, during, &amp; after her child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birth, and in ſomme, that shee remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned alwaies a Virgin vntill her death. It would follow alſo that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <note place="margin">Apoſtles and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triaches did not make the vovves of Religion.</note> and if wee pleaſe to aſcend higher, the Patriaches and Prophets, and he that participated of the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and qualities of the one and the other, S. Iohn Baptiſt the greateſt amongſt the children of men, should not haue beene in the ſtate of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, becauſe we do not reade that euer they made theſe vowes in which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:178129:27"/> they put the eſſence of the Regular life, albeit they had the practiſe of thoſe vertues in an eminent &amp; high degree. It would follow moreouer that ſo many millions of Monks which peopled the deſerts, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe actions almoſt inimitable wee ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reade without admiration, should not haue beene in this bleſſed ſtate, being that they were many yeeres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe two great law-makers of Regularitie, S. Baſile in the Orient, <note place="margin">S. Baſile, &amp; S. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net the firſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours of Regular cemmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties.</note> and S. Benet in the Occident, who firſt eſtablished lawes &amp; rules, for the gouernement of thoſe whom the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of perfecting themſelues in the Monaſticall diſcipline made to liue together in common. And then the vowes of theſe two rules were but ſimple vowes, diſpenſable according <note place="margin">Solemne vovves introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced but of late day as,</note> the will of the Superiours, the ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vowes being not introduced in the church, but in thoſe later ages, for a more ſure bond and tye of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Orders. Euen ſo did the Popes decide in our dayes in conſideration
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:178129:28"/> of the regular Clarks of the ſocietie of IESVS, that ſimple vowes are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to put him that makes them in the ſtate of perfection which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularitie doth promis, to the end that the yong Nouices of this holy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie, who make but the firſt vowes should haue the conſolation to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that they are in this honorall ſtate. But to diue more deeplie into the matter, if the vowes which giue precepts to ſuch as obſerue the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall counſells put them in the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of perfection, how shall the Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of S. Benet, S. Bernard and the <note place="margin">The vovves of Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctins, Ber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nardins &amp; Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſians.</note> Carthuſians, which make but vowes of ſtabilitie, &amp; of correcting their manners, without ſpecifying the vowes of chaſtitie, pouertie or obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, be in this ſtate of perfection? I know that the schoole Doctours do anſwere, that the promiſes of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe three Counſells are implicitè, as they ſpeake, contayned in the two vowes aforeſaid. But if ſo be, that in a contract there is no more force,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:178129:28"/> according the prouerb, then ſuch as men put in it, and that words are worth no more then as they ſound, how shall the ſtate of perfection be amongſt the Benedictins, the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſians and the Bernardins? We may ſay, that properly ſpeaking, that happie ſtate is not deſcended from heauen but ſince the Conuentuall Friars are deuided into more bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches then euer Xerxes deuided the riuer Gindes, &amp; that as many as will not put themſelues within their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke shall remaine in the Deluge of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection. I know well they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie, that for calling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars they do not hold that all other Chriſtians are irregular, that for cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling themſelues brothers, they do not ſeparat themſelues from the Frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of Chriſtianitie, nor do not take from the laitie that title which the <note place="margin">In the primitiue Church all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re called brothers.</note> firſt Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in the primitiue Church gaue to themſelues, that for calling themſelues Religious they do not hold other men to be irreligious &amp;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:178129:29"/> impious, that for being inrolled in particular Orders, they do not hold that other children of the Church doe liue in diſorder; but that their vowes putting them in a ſtate which doth oblige them to tend to a higher perfection, then that of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort, they haue reaſon to think that they are in the ſtate of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. To which I anſwere, that the ſtate of perfection is that, which approche neereſt to the imitation of the ſonne of God, of his moſt holy mother, &amp; of the holy Apoſtles, and that this imitation co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſting rather in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Euangelicall Counſells then in the vowes of them, that ſuch as are moſt aduaunced in thoſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are moſt perfect, &amp; in a more perfect eſtate then thoſe that only make vowes of them, and not practiſe them. And if they will ſay that a vow doth oblige him that makes it, to imbrace alſo the practiſe of it, &amp; to run in that ſort, as the Apoſtle ſaith, that he may arriue to the butt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:178129:29"/> of perfection; I will replie that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes it had beene better not to haue vowed, then after vowing to performe ſo ill their promiſe, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doe, for they may not mock God, but in the end they shall be punished for it: and the punishme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which he takes is ſo much the more ſeuere that it comes but ſlow. But they will ſay, that a vow added to the practiſe of the Counſells hath the ſame aduantage that faire appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, and pretious ſtones haue being added to an excellent beautie, which is neuer ſo exceſſiue in it owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture but the art of garments doth alwaies bring it more luſter; ſo a vow beſids the grace which it giues to a man, giues him alſo a certaine ſtable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; firmeneſſe, when he ſees himſelfe ingaged by theſe holy bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds to the ſeruice of God, from which he may not withdraw himſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out incurring, or as S. Paule ſaith, without acquiring his damnation. And I confeſſe ſo much, that a vow
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:178129:30"/> is a moſt holy and Religious action, &amp; that it is a ſtrong motiue, and a preſſing ſting to make a man run the race of perfection: but for a man to <note place="margin">Many did practiſe the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall vertues as vvell vvithout vovves as vvith vovves.</note> denie alſo that many men did as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectlie practiſe theſe vertues without vowes, it would be to draw vpon his owne back the examples, which we haue already produced of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, of his holy mother, of the Apoſtles, Patriarches, Prophets, and of the firſt Chriſtians, who were ſo perfect without that vow being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fundation of Monachiſme and Conuentuall life. Witneſſe that ancient Monke, who hauing conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med many yeeres to perfect himſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe in the exerciſe of the Euangelicall Counſells, had reuelation that the Emperour Theodoſius was equall to <note place="margin">Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect vvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout vovv.</note> him in merit, albeit according the Rule of Regulars he was not in the ſtate of their perfection: but he was a good Prince in the perfection of his owne eſtat, and whoſoeuer is ſo, according my ſimple iudgment may
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:178129:30"/> be ſaid to be in the ſtate of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And that which doth fortifie me in this thought is, that I do not find that the Scripture doth attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te perfection but to the practiſe of pouertie where it ſaith: <hi>If thou vvilt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 21.</note> 
               <hi>be perfect, goe, ſell the things that thou haſt, &amp; giue to the poore, and come, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv me.</hi> And S. Peter ſaying to our Sauiour that he had executed the counſell which he gaue to him and to his Condiſciples, doth not ſpeake of any vow, but of the effect of it by theſe words: <hi>Behold vve haue left all tbings, and haue follovved thee: vvhat therefore shall vve haue?</hi> To whom for reward our Sauiour did promis a hundred fold in this world, &amp; euerlaſting glorie in the other. I know well that a vow doth oblige a man to the practiſe of it, and alſo that it doth depriue a man of all proprietie, leauing him nothing but the ſimple vſe of things neceſſarie, according the ſaying of the Apoſtle: <hi>Hauing foode, and vvhervvith to be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.</note>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:178129:31"/> 
               <hi>couered, vvith theſe vve are content.</hi> And alſo I graunt that practiſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in vertue of a vow, is like vnto trees graffed, whoſe fruict are more ſweet, &amp; ſauorous, then that of other trees, but I know alſo, that as he that vow and effect it, shall be much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, ſo he that doth not execute what he promiſeth shall be doublie punished for hauing ingaged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in a combat which did not ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede with him, or to ſpeake with the Apoſtle, for hauing broken his word. And he that followes the Counſelles without obligation, if he be but ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie rewarded, he is not at all pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished when he failes, in ſort that it is written: <hi>Let him take it that can, he that imbraceth it doth vvell, &amp; he that doth not, doth not ill,</hi> in which conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth the difference betweene Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelles and precepts. And meditating with my ſelf vpon this ſubiect, I did often admeere, how it hapned that perfection was attributed in expreſſe termes to pouertie, and not to chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:178129:31"/> nor to obedience, conſidering that theſe two laſt vertues ſeeme to be ſo much the more excellent, by how much their ſubiect and obiect doth excell that of pouertie: for there is no doubt among men of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but that corporall goods, which are the pleaſures, to which men renounce by chaſtitie, and the goods of the ſoule, to which men bidd farewell by renouncing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and their proper wills, are of farr greater eſteemation and worth then are the goods of fortune, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of men depriue themſelues by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie: for who will denie that the ſoule is more pretious then meate, and the body more worth then it apparrell without he contradict, not only the Scripture but alſo common ſens? But if perfection conſiſt in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing our Sauiour, doth not he ſay? <hi>He that vvill fallo vv me let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luca</hi> 9. v. 23.</note> 
               <hi>himſelf, take vp his croſſe and follo vv me?</hi> And who is he that would not eaſier quitt what he doth poſſeſſe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:178129:32"/> then himſelf? toothe for toothe, and eye for eye, ſaith Iob, will man giue in counterchange of his ſoule, whoſe Sacrifice is made by obedience, obedience, which is better then all the Sacrifices of body and goods? That the practiſe of chaſtitie is a moſt perfect thing, it is very euident by that which the wiſman ſaith: <hi>That there is no price vvhich can equalla cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sap.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>and continent ſoule. O vvhat a faire &amp; excellent thing is, a generation full of puritie!</hi> And he that is more then Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, ſpeaking of thoſe volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Eunuches who gelded themſelues that they might the eaſier aſpire to heauen, doth not he ſay: <hi>That fevv</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 19 <hi>v.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>doth vnderſtand, and fevver doth exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe this vvord,</hi> shewing by the raritie of the practiſe the excellence of this vertue? In like manner, if I durſt ſay ſo, it ſeemeth that the vow and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of pouertie which is made out of a Commonaltie (which otherwiſe <note place="margin">A vovv of pouertie made out of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaltie vvhat it.</note> hath great merit, becauſe of the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience which double the goodneſſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:178129:32"/> of the action by the force of her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence) is more compleat, as shee is more difficile and hard, then that which is made within a ſocietie, where the one carrieth the burthen of the other, where they incourage &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort one an other, and to ſpeake with the Scripure, where the one doth heate the other in deuotion, and ſuccour his brother in his neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie by a mutuall ayde; in ſteade that a ſolitarie Monke, who ſells all that he hath, &amp; diſtribute it in almes, &amp; renounce all that he had, or might pretend in the world, to follow our Sauiour in that nakedneſſe, remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with this proppe without any other proppe but the eternall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, doth exerciſe more accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the letter (I cannot tell what he doth according the Spirit) the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of pouertie after the manner that it is laid downe in the Ghoſpell, then the other, where it is ſaid, that a man muſt quitt all that he hath and follow the ſonne of God in this abſolute
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:178129:33"/> nuditie, which hath no proppe in earth, and makes a man caſt all his thoughts on God. And who doth not ſee that he who renounceth his patrimonie, and puts himſelf into a Monaſterie well rented, or to a Conuent of begging friars, which probablie hath her maintenance at the gate for demaunding it; doth not often times paſſe from a litle and poore ſecular familie into a riche and well ſupported regular Monaſterie, where he is more aſſured that he shall want nothing that is neceſſarie for his maintenance, then if he had remayned in the world, where ſuch as are moſt fauoured by fortune, and that are moſt aduaunced in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours <note place="margin">The ſtate of fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</note> and richeſſe are ſubiect to ouerthrowes, to great falls, and to ſtrange deſaſters, and are like vnto thoſe falſe ſtarrs which fall and neuer get vp againe? In one word, it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cleere to ſuch as haue eyes, that as Conuentuall pouertie hath a luſter and an aduantage becauſe of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:178129:33"/> vow of it, ſo is shee alſo well rampared againſt the aſſaults of all misfortune, well refreſched by the help of many aſſiſtances, though tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe many times may be more cerimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious then compaſſionat. True po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie is that which indure with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience <note place="margin">True po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie vvhat is it.</note> the want of things neceſſarie; and to deſire to haue the glorie of this vertue without feeling the other points of neceſſitie, it is to deſire triumph and victorie without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, laurell and palme crownes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out putting himſelf to any hazard. Euerie body knowes that Ananias and Saphira for hauing ambitiouſlie deſired the honour to ſeeme poore like other Chriſtians, who did caſt all their goods without reſeruing any thing, at the feete of the Apoſtles, were ſtrucken with the anatheme of death by the Spirit of God paſſing out of the mouthe of the Prince of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. I know that the ſubti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hoole diuinitie, where the vertues, are refined as within a cruſet,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:178129:34"/> hath found out a number of faire reaſons to colour with a liuely, and pretious enamel the Conuentuall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, which, when all is ſaid, doth conſiſt in diſappropriating a man of the poſſeſſion of the goods wherof he retaines the vſage: but it happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s often that theſe determinations ſo diſtilled, do reſſemble thoſe quint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſens which turne into vapours as ſoone as they ſee the aire. For in <note place="margin">No man in this vvorld hath but the vſe of things.</note> fine who in this world can ſay that he is proprietaire of any thing, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that life it ſelf, without which all other goods, mouable and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouable are vnprofitable, is not giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs but in vſufruict, and not in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie? And to ſay that a man doth renounce to his life, but keeps onely the vſe of it, is it not to ſay that he quits that which he keepes, ſeing that life as well as richeſſe doth not conſiſt but in vſage?</p>
            <p>By this reconing Princes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lords who are inglutted in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and wealth ouer head and shoulders
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:178129:34"/> should be without vow in the ſtate of pouertie, ſeeing that like vnto the Conuentuall friars they haue but the vſe of their treaſures, &amp; that they do not handle it but by the hands of their treaſoriers, and ſuch other offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers; and the greateſt kings of the earth what haue they but their liuing in this world, and the vſe of the ſame ſunne and the ſame elements which the ſimpleſt Countryma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipat equallie with them? Yet for all that the regular Doctours do not graunt vnto them to be in the ſtate of perfection, albeit that in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture the ſoueraigne powers of the earth are putt in a ſtate of ſublimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. O how the firſt Monks proceeded after an other fashion, if not in vow, at leaſtwiſe in the practiſe of pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, for after hauing ſold &amp; diſtributed to the poore their patrimonie, they did caſt themſelues into the deſerts, flying from the world as well in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy as in hart and minde, and there afflicted, neceſſitous and miſerable,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:178129:35"/> to vſe Apoſtolik termes, they retired the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues into caues and holes within the earth, imitating our Sauiour, who during his life had not a place to put in his head, hauing no houſe of his owne, no Cloiſter, no cell, no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent nor any other thing, which he might call his owne, but the croſſe, which he carried vpon his shoulders to Mont Caluaire. Alas! when shall that happie time come, in which the Monks, Anacorites and friars will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſcitat in themſelues the Spirit of that great Apoſtle, which may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to gaine their liuing by the labours of their hands, and to eate their bread with ashes, by the ſweate of their browes, without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſting <note place="margin">Monks &amp; friars should rather vvorke for their liuing then begg</note> this man or that man, ſome ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes by begging of almes from doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to doore, ſome times importunat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie demaunding fundations for their Monaſteries, and ſome times taking dowries, as they do in Nunries; &amp; to ſpeake in ſacred termes, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore irreprehenſible, making lucre of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:178129:35"/> pietie &amp; buſying the ſimpler ſort to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Titi</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 12.</note> draw profit to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues &amp; doing like the liuer, which doth not become fatt, but by the leanneſſe of other members? I haue not beene a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 20.</note> to any man, ſaith S. Paul glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</note> himſef in God, but teaching, preaching and labouring, I haue by <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.</note> the work of my ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds prouided what <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.</note> was needfull for me. So did, ſo liued theſe ancient Anacoretes, who made basketts &amp; other ſmall works which they carried to the market to be ſold, to nourrish themſelues with the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of them, &amp; to giue the ſurplus to the poore. So did alſo the ancient Regulars, as may be eaſelie ſeene in <note place="margin">Ancient regulars liued by their labour.</note> the Chronicles of the Orders, who liued in the ſeruice of God, and in the obſeruance of their rules, tilling the earthe, digging and labouring the vine-yards, gayning their daylie wages during the harueſt and the ventage, and bringing all to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaltie, without reſeruing any thing to themſelues in particular,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:178129:36"/> vnder paine of excommunication, and to be buried, if they were found dying, poſſeſſours of any thing whatſoeuer, in the ſepulchers of beaſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cutting the woods, drying vp marrish grounds, playing the joyners, and the carpenters, building of houſes, keeping of cattle and doing all other Countrie huſbandrie: the weaker ſort giuing themſelues to thoſe arts which are leſſe painefull, as to play the taylours, the paintu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, working, of wooll, &amp; coppying of books, before printing became ſo common. In this ſort euerie one did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tribut his paine without any other reward to himſelf, but the abondance which is promiſed in heauen. The millions of Monks which liued in Monaſteries did infinit good to the neighbours about them, in ſteed of incommodating &amp; oppreſſing them as now ſome do, they made themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues by their labourious induſtries the Fathers of the poore, being themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues poore in all reſpects. I do not
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:178129:36"/> intend by this to blame the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes of the church (knowing that all extremities are vitious and incline to errour) ſo they be moderat: for if moderation in all things is to be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, in this kind it is not only praiſe worthy, but in ſome ſort neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the experience of ſo many ages making vs to ſee and feele that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe doth carrie men to abuſes and licentiouſneſſe, that I ſay no worſe; and as S. Bernard ſaith, that if ſo be deuotion doth ingender richeſſe, theſe bad daughters when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come great doth ſuffocat &amp; ſtifle their mother, and induce her to ſinne, as Loth that was ſo holy was induced by his owne daughters. Much leſſe do I intend to blame mendicitie or begging, conſidering that my ſelf doth make profeſſion of it, and knowing that it hath beene deuout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie permitted in the church, and that ſuch as cried againſt the begging Orders of S. Francis and S. Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick when they were newly inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:178129:37"/> were conſtrained to imbrace the ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which was impoſed to them by the ſoueraigne Bishop the Pope. But it is to be wished, that this me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicitie should not be vſed but to ſupplie the default of manuel labour, when <note place="margin">Begging is to be vſed vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not gett their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing by their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</note> after a diligent imploy they should find themſelues short of meanes to nourish the Commonaltie: for in that caſe they might vſe the priuiledg of the law of nature, which permit euerie man to aske his liuing when he cannot labour for it. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce that to a forme or fashio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is ordayned by the rules of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſterie touching corporall labour, towards the incloſures of gardens, which they till rather, for the health and pleaſure of particular perſons, then for the profit and vtilitie of the houſe, and rather to haue flowers to deck and adorne the altars then to haue fruict to putt vpon the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; is in my opinion to make a delicat Sabath at the chardges of the common wealth, whom it concernes
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:178129:37"/> that euery body labour, and make vſe and profit of his talent, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie, in manuring the vigneyard, that is to ſay, in following the voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which fell to his lott, according the line of diuine diſtribution. The Emperour Diocletian hauing putt of <note place="margin">The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Diocletia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did vvork</note> the Empire, tooke great paines to trim and dreſſe his litle garden, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſweetlie his time in the innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t imploy of tilling the ground, and after that fashion he ſaw himſelf as riche in his pouertie, as before being in his Emperiall dignitie, he found himſelf poore in the middeſt of his richeſſe, hauing not alwaies wherby to recompence worthelie ſuch as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him well, nor to pay his armies. It is not that in this occaſion, I would iuſtifie my ſelf, conſidering that I was conceiued in iniquitie, and that I am all rotten with vitious cicatri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and much leſſe would I preferr my ſelf to thoſe whoſe shooe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chets, I am not worthy to looſe. But I may aſſure you, that I do not begg
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:178129:38"/> in theſe quarters but in as much as my infirmities do take from my ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes the pouer to trauaile, hauing ſeene my ſelf ſometimes of that force and vigour, that I had by my owne induſtrie the meanes, not only to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine my ſelf without chardging any other, but alſo to intertaine others that came to viſit this cell. And if now neceſſitie doth conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne me to haue recours ſometimes to the charitie of thoſe to whom, I gaine heauen through the good which they do vnto me, my age and my weakneſſe doth pleade my cauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their pietie, &amp; make them har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to my petition.</p>
            <p>Here Triſtan, as in a place which to him ſeemed very proper to offer his goods to Nicephorus, breaking the cours of his long diſcours; Father, ſaith he, the prouidence of God hath conducted me hither, and to ſpeake otherwiſe, hath leade me by the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of his will, to draw you out of all paine, and your old yeeres from care
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:178129:38"/> and labour. I haue by the grace of God abondantly to maintaine you without ſuffocating your Spirit by bodely labour, and putting your ſelf to trouble to ſearche your lyuing. Sir, quoth the Hermite, if I had not knowne in your face your ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the ſinceritie of your inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the offer which you make vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, I would make you the ſame anſwere which our Sauiour made to S. Peeter, who would faine diſſwade him from going to ſuffer to Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem wherof he heard him ſpeake to Moyſes &amp; Elias vpon mont Thabor: Retire from me Sathan. What? you are then come hither to tempt me to deſcend from the croſſe of holy pouertie, in which I deſire to die, in the nuditie and nakedneſſe of my Sauiour. Ha! not ſo Sir, nothing shall ſeparat me if I can from the charitie of IESVS CHRIST, not death nor life, not hunger, not cold, not nuditie, not pouertie nor want, not me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor Angelles, not the powers
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:178129:39"/> of the earth nor that of hell, not the time paſt, nor the time preſent, nor the time to come: For I am certaine with the help of his grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine conſtant in my reſolution, and neuer to relent in any one point of it: I meane to die poore with him that being riche made himſelf poore for our ſakes, to the ende to inriche vs by his want. Labour taken for him is no labour, for he made the yoke of his croſſe ſo ſweet and eaſie by the oyle of his bloude which is baulme shedd for vs, that his bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then is rather a ſolagement then a chardge, reſembling the feathers of birds which lift them vp to the ayre in ſteed of waighing them downe to the earthe. There is no paine where there is loue, or if there be any, it is but a deare and deſirable paine; for to labour for that which a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loueth, of all delices it is the ſweeteſt. And if you think that manuel labour doth diſſipat the Spirites (that which ſome delicat fellowes ſaid, vnworthy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:178129:39"/> of a heade all torne with thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarywiſe, I hold that it doth rather fortifie it, witneſſe the Apoſtle <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 10.</note> ſaying, that his Spirit was then moſt vigorours and ſtrong when his body was ouercommed and weakned by infirmities, or by voluntarie morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications; and I feare much that ſuch as ſay that manuel labour might cauſe the diſſipation of their Spirit do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d more the diſſipation of their bodys, and as S. Paul ſaith, the diſſipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this machine &amp; terreſtriall ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which inuirone the ſoule. For eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the nobilitie which in peace ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me do reſerue for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſlouth &amp; idleneſſe, and in warr time the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of armes. In like manner it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that theſe fathers more conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>platiue then actiue do confine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the ſinging of Pſalmes, as if it were a function very laborious to ſing, or that it had beene the harp of Dauid to chaſe away the Diuells of vice by her melodie, which poſſeſſe ſinners, or that it had the force of the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:178129:40"/> Sacerdotall tro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petts, at whoſe ſound did fall the walls of Hiericho, or of the hands of Moyſes which gaue vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie to the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſraëll againſt Amalec. Certes, if by the effects we may iudge of the vigour and force of the cauſe, we may well ſay of their Congregations that which the ſacred Cantique doth ſay of the Sulamite, what will you ſee in her but Quires of combattants and ſquadrons of Choriſters? It is there they take that ſweet and pleaſant ſleepe vpon the breaſt of our Sauiour, from which, no leſſe then the Amant and louer of the ſame ſpouſe would they be drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or waked, vntill it pleaſe themſelues to paſſe from the eaſe and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this ſacred contemplation to the action, &amp; from the ſweet attentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Marie to the tumultuous labours of Martha; in the meane time the litle ones demaund bread, &amp; few do breake it vnto them; the neighbours do grone and waile, &amp; few do ſuccour them: many are wounded vpon the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:178129:40"/> way of Hiëricho and there are but few Samaritans that would ſolace <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 34.</note> and comfort them. The Countries are white to harueſt, and there are but few harueſt-men: the vigne-yard is deſert and vntilled, and there are but few venteners, much worke and few workmen. <note place="margin">The three principall functions of an Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonne.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Of the three principall functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the Eccleſiaſticall ſtate, which are to preach, to adminiſter the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and to pray, be it in particular men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally, or vocally; be it in publick by ſinging of the publike office, the greateſt part of the friars toke this laſt, which is the moſt ſpeciouſe and leſſe profitable, for the lott of their inheritance, and for their imployme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſaying with the Pſalmiſt: <hi>I vvill ſing your iuſtices o lord, in this ſejour of my pilgrimage.</hi> And in effect, when all shall be well counted, for three or foure which announce to the people the word of God, which is the breade of life and vnderſtanding, for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of which the Apoſtles
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:178129:41"/> themſelues did ceaſe from diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſacred communion, which the holy text doth call to ſerue to the tables, there are fiftie or three ſcoare in great Conuents deputed only for the Quire, and fifteene or twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie lay brothers tyed to the dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall functions. But perchance they will ſay that they imploy the Friars according the talents which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from God, it being very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable that in the Church which is a terreſtriall Paradis, the trees do beare fruict according their kind, &amp; that men do worke according their qualities, and that the tallent of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching or of helping ſoules, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire great ſcience and prudence in diſcerning of Spirits, being giuen but to a few, there are many more that are capable of the Quire then of the chaire. To which I anſwere that ſuch as are proper for the Quire ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be vnproper for manuel labour, and that percha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the weale publique would be as much content and ſolaged by
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:178129:41"/> their labour as by their ſinging. It is not that I call in doubt the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of prayer, and that I do not know that men may ſay of her what that ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t painteur ſaid of his owne worke, that shee labours for the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and that shee hath this aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage ouer mechanicall things, that theſe being viſible are conſequentlie te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall as the Apoſtle ſaith, &amp; that the other which is inuiſible, as that of prayer; is eternall. But if in this age men eſteeme more of ſinſible the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſpiritual things, none being in it which doth not preferr almeſdeeds to prayer, &amp; alſo to faſting; it may be ſaid that manuell labour which doth neceſſarily nourishe a poore man, as he is, that worke of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, shall not be leſſe eſtimable then prayer, and that the worke of thoſe hands wherof the great Apoſtle did glorifie himſelf, shall not be leſſe eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med then was his rauishment to the third heauen, a fauour which ſerued him rather for recompence then for
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:178129:42"/> merit. Hence is it, that he doth name himſelf in the one and not in the other, as hauing ſome part in the one and none in the other, which arriued to him by a gratuit grace, ſuch as reuelation is, and the gift of Prophecie. By reaſon of which the Pſalmiſt doth call happie, not thoſe that are euerie-day in extaſie, but thoſe that maintaine themſelues by the ſweate of their browes.</p>
            <p>Peraduenture ſome will ſay that the particular office of Monks, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording <note place="margin">The par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular office of a Monke.</note> S. Hierome, is to weepe &amp; to pray, and that the functions to preach and to adminiſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are not for them but in way of ſupererogation, that they might not fall into the reproche which is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in the Ghoſpell to the prieſt and Leuite, who did not ſuccour him that was left for deade by the theeues that thought to murther him in the high way. But ſeeing that the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference which men put betweene Monks &amp; Religious men, is drawne
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:178129:42"/> from that, that Monks do not applie themſelues, or ought not to applie themſelues by their inſtitution but to the ſolitarie and pure contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue life, and that the Religious do not applie themſelues to prayer on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but alſo to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templation, making as our Sauiour and the Apoſtles did, a kind of life called a mixt life, of action and contemplation, by which, as by Iacobs ladder, ſome times they lift themſelues vp to God by prayer, ſometimes they deſcend towards the neighbour by the works of mercie; a life which the ſcholaſticall diuinitie, grounded vpon great reaſons, eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the moſt perfect; it should follow that ſuch as call themſelues Religious men, and that obtayned of the ſoueraigne Bishop ſo many exemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and priuiledges, that they might exerciſe Clericall or Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall functions for the ſeruice of ſoules, should attend more to ſowe the ſacred word, &amp; to adminiſter the Sacraments, then to the exerciſe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:178129:43"/> of the Quire, which is more conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for Monks then for them. And ſeeing that none doth enter their Orders, but by the choice and trial which they make of ſuch as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelues to them, they should not receiue any but ſuch as should haue the talents neceſſarie for the functions of the mixt life, which they ſay, as the moſt perfect, to be confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to their inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to their ſtate of perfection. In this manner the commonwealth should be more ſolaged by their labours then by their clamours; for to tell no lye, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, as ſaid great S. Charles of his owne time, that as the Church of this our age tormented by Libertins and Hereticks, hath more neede of good Paſtours then of good Religious <note place="margin">The church hath mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re neede of good Paſtours then of good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious men.</note> men, ſo hath shee more neede amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Religious men of thoſe that are peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of action, then of ſingers &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templatiues, and of Champions then of Choriſters: for albeit Marie choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the beſt part for her, it is not for
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:178129:43"/> all that the beſt alwaies for the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, &amp; albeit it is the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent part, yet is it not the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable. And if they should alleage Moyſes praying, and Ioſüé with ſo many thouſands Iſraëlites fighting, the obiection will carrie it owne an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere with it ſelf, ſeing that for one that lift vp his hands praying, thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of others do exerciſe their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds againſt the enemies. Which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie with the Regulars, who for a hundred that ſing in the Quire haue not two that take paines to deſcend to the ſuccour of the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and of the church, forſaking the mountaine of prayer, a fatt moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, a mountaine of creame, a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine all of honny, where it pleaſeth them to remaine with God in peace, rather then in warr among the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combrances which are found in the <note place="margin">Regulars vvould not take the pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that Paſtours do.</note> tabernacles of ſeculars and Paſtours. Euen ſo ſome ſinners who cannot draw themſelues from their badd ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitudes, and who deferr their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:178129:44"/> till the time of their death do make a badd buckler of the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the good theefe, who conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf vpon the croſſe, and the very ſame day entred into Paradis according the promis of our Sauiour: becauſe, that for that one man that was ſaued in that point, thouſands and thouſands are loſt and damned, it being very reaſonable ſaith S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin, that he doth forget himſelf dying, who lyuing did not reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber to returne to God. Euen ſo the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards in their Solemnities, becauſe that Dauid danced once before the Arke by an exceſſe of pietie, and by an extraordinarie motion of the holy Ghoſt, would not think to make a good proceſſion if there were not dancers in it.</p>
            <p>That is the ſame thing, quoth Triſtan, which ſome Religious men ſaid to me, to whom I did communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat the deſſigne which I had to retire my ſelf to an Hermitage; that Monks were not good but for themſelues,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:178129:44"/> but Religious men are neceſſarie for the Chriſtian common wealth, which is the church. To which Nicephorus replied, if by Monks they vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the Hermites which applie themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues ſoly &amp; ſimplie to contemplation, and of which men call Anacorites, they haue ſome apparance of reaſon, but if to preach, to catechiſe, to viſit the ſick, to attend to the conuerſion of the ſtrayed, to adminiſter the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of pennance and the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, &amp; to do all things according the commaund of the Ordinarie, and vnder the imploy of the Paſtours, do make a Religious man, many Hermites will be found, which will be no more Monks, but Religious men, and many Conuentuall Friars, which do nothing of all theſe things, shall be no Religious men but Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks. And to shew vnto you that it is not in that point that this bleſſed diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a Monke &amp; a Religious man doth conſiſt; But in I know not what imagination, which I conceiue as litle
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:178129:45"/> as I do the Ideas of Plato, and the atomes of Dimocrites; The Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctins, the Bernardins, the Celeſtins, the Fueillantins, and thoſe of the Order of S. Baſile, to whom they giue the name of Monks, as being at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to them by their rules, do not they liue in Conuents, do not they preach, do not they teach the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian doctrine, do not they admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Sacraments in vertue of ſo many indults and ſo many immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Bulls as they haue from the Sea Apoſtolique? in ſort as I do not ſee, neither in their liues, nor in their <note place="margin">Monks do not differ from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentuall Friars.</note> functions in what they differ from the Conuentuall Friars who call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues Religious men. The differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce is not in mendicitie for there are Conuentuall Friars which call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues Religious men who are not beggers: it is not in abſtinence from meate, for in that the Minimes are more auſtere then the Benedictins or Celeſtins, yea, or the Carthuſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s themſelues: it is not in mendicitie &amp;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:178129:45"/> abſtinence together, for in that the Reformed Dominicans and the bare <note place="margin">The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s differ much fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate.</note> footed Carmelits are admirable in abſtayning fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vſe of fleſche, they liuing but by almes. And to ſay what I think, I ſee ſo litle difference, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene thoſe whom they call Monks aboue named, and the Conuentuall Friars be they beggers, or not beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, shodd or not shodd, that I think men may call Monks Religious men by as iuſt a title, as they call Religious men Monks; and I muſt graunt vnto you that, I am not ſo ſubtile nor ſo penetratiue as he that found ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene eſſentiall differences betweene the habit of the Capucins and that of the Tertiarians which men call Regular Penitens of the third order <note place="margin">Seue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences found betvvee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of the Capucins &amp; that of the Tier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiarians.</note> of S. Francis of ſtrict Obſeruance. To ſay that the differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce doth conſiſt in the vowes, I ſee no apparance of it, becauſe the three eſſentiall vowes of Religion, which are the three Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall conſells, are common to all orders as well Monks as Religious
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:178129:46"/> men. In this ſort I do not ſee that the name Monke may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly attributed to any but to the Carthuſians, to the Friars of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of Camaldoli, and to ſome shutt vp Anacoretes, becauſe of their ſilence, of their incloſure, and of their ſolitarineſſe, which interdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them the commerce of men, doth alſo take from them all Cleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call functions, for which the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentuall Friars called themſelues Religious men. And for the word Regular, it is certaine that as many as make profeſſion of any rule do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, as do theſe new Congregations of Clearkes which are called Regulars to the imitation of the Chanon Regulars which liue vnder the rule of S. Auſtin, Wherof I remember being in Rome, which is the nurcerie of all theſe Orders as being the matrice of the Church, to haue obſerued ſeuen ſortes, without counting the prieſts of the Oratorie, <note place="margin">Seue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſorts of Clekes Regulars</note> called of our ladie of the white-well,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:178129:46"/> or of Vallicelles, inſtituted by ſainct Philip Nerio Florentin, and the Oblats of S. Ambroſe, founded by S. Charles, and the prieſts of the Oratorie of IESVS, whoſe Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation ſprong vp in France are almoſt all Frenchmen, powre out a ſweet odoure of ſainctitie and vertue throught all the French Church, &amp; begins to extend it branches, like a vigne planted neere the Oliues of grace, to forraine Countries.</p>
            <p>Is it poſſible, quoth Triſtan, that there are ſo many ſorts of Regular Clearks, wheras there are but foure ſorts of begging Orders? I told you that I obſerued ſeuen ſeuerall inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of them while I was in Italie, and I know not but ſince there is ſome other new fashion ſprong vp. If my memorie doth not faile me, I beleeue I shall name them well yet. The Theatins are the firſt for the date of the time, inſtituted by the right Reuerend Father in God Iohn Peeter Carraffe Bishop of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:178129:47"/> Thiette, who renounced his Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoprick, to lead a kind of life truely Apoſtolicall, with ſome prieſts which did aſſociate themſelues to him, renouncing all things as well in common as in particular, adding this point to the ſtrict pouertie of begging Orders, that albeit they liue onely by almes, yet do they neuer begg <note place="margin">A ſtrange inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Theatins.</note> neither by themſelues nor by any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſed perſons, caſting all their thoughts vpon the paternall care of the prouidence of God concerning their maintenance, and putting in practiſe according the litterall ſens this Euangelicall Counſell, not to think of to morrow, nor of that which is neceſſarie for foode or cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, imitating therin the Lyllis of the fields, and the birds of the aire, which God doth cloathe and feede without that they ſpinne or labour themſelues for it. This Bishop, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutour of this holy Congregation, after hauing illuminated &amp; ſeaſoned all the Court of Rome with the light
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:178129:47"/> and ſalt of his Doctrine, and of his good life, was eleuated from the preambular dignitie of Cardinall to that of the ſoueraigne Bishop, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing the Sea Apoſtolique vnder the name of Paul the third. The vulgar ſort named theſe Regular Clerkes Theatins, in ſteed of calling them Thietins, as who would ſay, the Clerkes of the Inſtitution of the Bishop of Thiette. They haue many houſes in Italie, and I know not if they exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d themſelues elſwhere, this much I know, that as yet wee haue not ſeene of them in France, where it is to be thought they should be ill addreſſed if they would not aske or begg, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering that ſuch as do begg do often find their almes very short, ſuch is the humour of our Nation, which haue their hands open for vaine expenſes and prodigalities, and shutt vp to iuſt and holy liberalities, by which doth appeere that the end of the world will come by that way ſeing charitie is growen ſo cold
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:178129:48"/> in it. Which is not in Italy, where men beleeue more firmely then we do, that ſinne is redeemed by almeſdeeds, and that by this lauor or font all their filth &amp; ordure are clenſed. The ſecond inſtitution of Regular Clearkes is that of the prieſts of the ſocietie of IESVS, of which, as that ancient writer ſaid of the magnifice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Rome, it is better ſay nothing then ſay litle, being ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that this holy ſocietie is praiſed by the mouthe of the holy Counſell of Trent, which is that of the holy Ghoſt, ſaying that their inſtitution is praiſe worthie. The Barnabites doth make the third inſtitution; this Order tooke it origine in Millan, the ordinarie reſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their Generall, and they are ſo called, becauſe that the firſt Church where they did aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble together was called of ſainct Barnabe, euen as the Friars Preachers of the Order of ſainct Dominick are called Iacobins in Paris, becauſe of a Chappell of S. Iake, otherwiſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:178129:48"/> Iames where they firſt loadged. The Clerkes Mineurs, which are of the inſtitution of Pope Sixtus V. who was of the Order of the Friars Mineurs, do make the fourthe ſort. The fift is of the Sommaſques, a name ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſtrange to ſuch as do not know the origine of it, which is, that this Congregation of Regular Clearkes was inſtituted by a gentilman of Veniſe in the marche of Treuiſane, in a bourg called Sommaſcha. So that as the Chartreux or Carthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians were ſo called of the place called Chartreuſe, where they made their firſt aboade, and where is the Capitall houſe of their Order, as the Cluniacenſes were called of the towne Clugny, the Ciſtercienſes of Ciſteaux, Camaldu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenſes of Camaldoli, euen ſo did the Sommaſques receiue their nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the place where they were firſt eſtablished. Theſe do extend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in Italy &amp; in France vnder the title of Fathers of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:178129:49"/> Doctrine whoſe houſes are renowned in Prouance, Languedoc and Guenne. The Sixt inſtitution is of Regular Clearks ſurnamed the Infirmes, becauſe their chardg is, to ſerue the ſick, be it within the publick Hoſpitalls or in priuat houſes, &amp; alſo to ſuccour ſuch as are moſt miſerable and forſaken. The ſeuenth is that of the Regular Clerks of the mother of God, called the Congregation of the prieſts of Lucques, wherof Father Franciotti, who wrote ſo deuotely, hath beene one of the principall pillars.</p>
            <p>And that which is admirable in this varietie of inſtitutions is, that they are all particular rules, which leuell at ſome particular marke; the Theatins do applie themſelues to ſtudy and to leade a retired life; the Ieſuits to inſtruict youthe; the Barnabites to the Quire and to heare Confeſſions; the Clearks Mineurs to the rigour and auſteritie of morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications; the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maſques to keepe S.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:178129:49"/> and maintaine forſaken Children, &amp; Orphans, and to teache the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Doctrine; The Clearks of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme to looke to the ſick, and the Clearkes of the mother of God, to direct deuote people to ſpirituall things. This notwithſtanding they haue all but the ſelf ſame habit, which is that wee ſee the Ieſuits carrie. All of them make profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a certaine rule with the ſolemne vowes, and call themſelues Religious men, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in this from the Conuentuall Friars, that theſe vnder different ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits do make but the ſelf ſame thing, and the other do make differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions vnder a like habit. In ſort that the one and the other coming to the ſuccour of the Paſtours do exerciſe <note place="margin">All thoſe Regular Orders came to ſuccour the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours.</note> Clericall functions, which heretofore was not affected or ordayned but for the prieſts of the Eccleſiaſticall Cleargie, ſome of them may be called Religious Clearks, others Clearks Religious, and all of them are comprehended vnder the Name
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:178129:50"/> of Regulars. Beſids, all the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, which liue vnder the rule of ſainct Auguſtin, who are very many, do call themſelues Clearkes Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, as thoſe of the Order of ſainct Anthonie, of ſainct Ruf, of Val de Choux, of Val des Eſcoliers, the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians, the Friars de la Mercy, the Hieromites, the Dominicans, and ſo many other Militarie Orders which haue this rule for the line of their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and obſeruance.</p>
            <p>Why do you put the Dominicans, ſaith Triſtan, among the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, or Regular Clearks, wheras they are one of the foure begging Orders? If you number, quoth the Hermit, the begging Orders accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their rules there are but three ſorts of them, for the Dominicans and the Auſtin Friars haue but the ſelf ſame rule, albeit their habits and conſtitutions do differ; the Friars Mineurs haue the rule of S. Francis, and the Carmelits that of ſainct Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſile, or of the Patriarche Albertus.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:178129:50"/> But if you take them according their Congregations, the begging Orders do farr exceede the number of foure; <note place="margin">Of the rule of S. Francis there are ten ſorts.</note> the only rule of ſainct Francis doth fournish ten ſorts of them: The Cordeliers called Obſeruantins; the Conuentualls called the great Friars, which begg almoſt euery where, albeit they may haue rents; the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colects of ſtrict Obſeruance, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pucins, the Becquins, the Tertiarians; the Religious women of S. Clare, who hath a particular rule framed by S. Francis, which are ſubdiuided into Damianiſts &amp; Vrbaniſts, beſids the Capucin wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and the Hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts of ſainct Francis, in ſort that men may ſay the ten begging Orders of Francis. Add to this the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicans, as well the Mitigated as the Reformed; the Friars Hermites of ſainct Auſtins Order as well the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigated as the Reformed, the shodd as the vnshodd: In like manner the Carmelits as well the Mitigated, and the vnshodd of the reformation of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:178129:51"/> S. Tereſa, as the Reformed shodd; the Friars Hoſpitaliſts of the Charitie inſtituted by S. Iohn de Dieu; the Ieſuates inſtituted by ſainct Iohn Colomban; the Minimes, which are put among the begging Orders, as are alſo the profeſſed Ieſuits of the laſt vow, the Theatins, the Clearks Mineurs, the Clearks of the Infirme, the Friars de la Mort, and the moſt part of the Hermites; beſids many others which are ſeene in Italy beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging after diuers manners, as thoſe that are called <hi>Fate ben Fratelli,</hi> and thoſe that crie asking almes: <hi>Faciamo bene mentre che hauemo tempo,</hi> and ſuch like, in ſort that according the count which we haue now made, not ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of that wherof we are ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, wee should not ſay the foure but the nyne and twentie Mendicant Orders. To which if you will add ſuch as liue by rents and fundations, you shall find a litle armie of Regulars, of which men may ſay what Iacob ſaid of the Angels, theſe are the ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:178129:51"/> of the God of battles. Now to know among ſo many people, who are they whom wee may call Monks without offending them, and who are to be called Religious men, it is no ſmall matter, and to do it without danger of miſtaking, a man muſt know many particularities and many hiſtories, which is cauſe that men, to eſchew all thoſe formalities, do call all Regulars Religious men, &amp; that the rather that all true Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks are very glad to be ſo called, and that ſuch as hold themſelues to be Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men, do take it for an outrage and inciuilitie, when men call them Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks. Which make me call to mind our gentilwomen who are very glad when men through errour do call them Dames, and our grand-Dames who could not indure that men should call them Gentilwomen, no more then thoſe prieſts who will not haue themſelues called Clearks. In what then, replied Triſtan, doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt this ſtate of perfection of which
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:178129:52"/> all Monaſticall and Conuentuall perſons, Monks or Religious men, call them as you pleaſe, do make ſo great account, and from which they ſay you Hermites are ſo farr, as you can neuer pretend it?</p>
            <p>For my part, quoth Nicephorus, I beleeue they are as well grounded in the poſſeſſion of the ſtate of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as they are in the title of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious men. Thoſe that are called in the Acts of the Apoſtles, Religious men, were deuote perſons in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church, which were neither Monks nor Regulars; and all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians which liue according the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the Ghoſpell, and of the Catholike Religion, eſtablished by IESVS CHRIST ſeemeth to me to haue right to call themſelues Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious <note place="margin">All good Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s may be called Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious men.</note> men, though they be lay and married men, and what other trade they be of. And that it is ſo, who doth not know that S. Francis wrote a third Rule of pennance, in which all faithfull people of what ſex or
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:178129:52"/> condition ſoeuer they be may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled, and carrie the qualitie of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious men of the third Order of this Seraphicall Father? Yea but, replied Triſtan, thoſe Religious men are not in the ſtate of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the others are which make the three vowes conformable to the Euangelicall Counſells: for me thinks the ſaid Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſaid to me, that it is in that that this ſtate of perfection doth conſiſt, from which the Hermits are exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. At this word excluded, the bloud mounted to the Hermits face, &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured it, if not for ſpite and cholar, at leaſtwiſe for confuſion and emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This then made him replie in this ſort: if wee be excluded, it is with good companie, for beſids that we do not read, as I ſaid alreadie, that our Sauiour, his holy mother, and the Apoſtles euer made the ſaid vowes, well wee reade that they practiſed the holy vertus counſelled in the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell; and by this practiſe they arriued both to the perfection of their eſtate,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:178129:53"/> and to te ſtate of an eminent perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; they muſt exclude with vs all the Chanons of the Cathedrall and Collegiall Churches, all the Paſtours &amp; venerable Prieſts which are in the Church and haue no other rule but the rule of rules which is the holy Ghoſpell, to the line and ſquare of which all other rules should be fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be made right. Behold then wee are in good companie, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, Doctours, and Preachers, if they do not vow vnder a certaine rule, they shall not be in the ſtate of perfection, they that are the ſalt of the earthe, &amp; the light of the world. And a lay Brother that <note place="margin">A hard cenſure.</note> beggs yp and downe, that playes the Cooke, and the gardener in a Conuent, shall be in a more eminent ſtate in the Church of God then all thoſe people. A man without doubt muſt be well verſed in the ſubtilities of the ſchole to comprehend this Diuinitie, very hard to be inculcated to ignorant men. Let vs mount our
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:178129:53"/> ſtring to a higher note, and ſay that the Bishops, the Cardinalles and the Pope himſelf shall not be in this ſtate of perfection, hauing not vowed the obſeruance of any of theſe rules ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by the Cburch, vnder which the Regulars are inrolled.</p>
            <p>To this the Regulars do replie, quoth Triſtan, that thoſe Paſtours are in a ſtate of perfection more eminent then that of the Religious, in ſo much as they call it the ſtate of perfection <note place="margin">Bishops are in the ſtate of perfection acquired.</note> acquired, and the other but a ſtate of perfection to be acquired. So that they are the ſunne which comprend in their light all the light of the leſſer ſtarrs: and the firmame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the earth lifted vp ouer the topp of the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taignes of perfection, whoſe fruict do extend it ſelf farr ouer mount Liban, where theſe puiſſant Gods of the earth are ſtronglie placed, becauſe they are the children of the higheſt, and his arrowes in the hand of the Omnipotent, which flee out with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuoſitie. This is the eſtate which is
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:178129:54"/> called the ſupreme amongſt men in the militant Church, which correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pond to that of the Seraphins in the <note place="margin">They cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to the Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phins in the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie.</note> firſt Hierarchie of the Angelles. In ſort that as the rodd of Moyſes did ſwallow vp the rodd of the Magitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, euen ſo in the eſtate of Prelatship &amp; Pontificat are contayned all the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of all the Regular Orders, in the ſame manner that Prieſthood doth containe in it ſelf the inferiour Orders. But my difficultie is to know in what doth conſiſt this diſtinction betweene perfection acquired, and perfection to be acquired; for I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that the greateſt part of the world are in the laſt, and but very few in the other. For to ſay a perfect man, is to ſay a man without ſinne, and he that ſaith he hath no ſinne, is a lyer and hath no truth in him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording the holy Scripture: <hi>Vvho thinks to be vvithout ſinne doth ſeduce himſelf, for vvee are all conceiued in iniquitie.</hi> To ſay alſo with that Bishop of the Apocalyps lo: <hi>I am full of</hi>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:178129:54"/> 
               <hi>grace, and haue no neede of any thing,</hi> is to ſay, I am in the topp of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and conſequently to get this reproche: <hi>Thou art naked, poore &amp; miſerable, &amp; foolishlie you eſteeme your ſelf riche.</hi> For I hold that man to be very imperfect that thinks himſelf to be perfect; it is in a manner to ſay as ſaid the father of the proud: <hi>I Will lift vp my throne of the North ſide, and I shall be like to the higheſt.</hi> Behold ſo much for the perfection acquired, &amp; for the perfection to be acquired, it is a condition wherin are thoſe that are moſt imperfect, ſeeing that at the moſt it ſuffiſeth them to haue the will to arriue ſome time to it when they shall be purged of their faults, and for men to vant themſelues to be riche, either by the goods, which they deſire to haue, or pretend to gather, is expreſſe vanitie. And by this eſtate to think to draw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from all paritie, and to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated <note place="margin">Friars in their ovvne eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are not like other men.</note> from the reſt of the lay or ſecular people, it is in ſome ſort to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:178129:55"/> ſing that ſong blamed in te Ghoſpell: <hi>I am not like other men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, quoth the Hermite, I ſee well that neither you nor my ſelf are too well verſed in theſe ſcholaſticall ſubti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, this is a wrangling point which is not good but to intertaine diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vpon the ſtooles; it is properly according the prouerb to conteſt with the Bishop for his croſiers ſtaffe. But as I heard ſay heretofore, they put great difference betwene the ſtate of perfection acquired, or to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, &amp; perfection it ſelfe, be it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired or to be acquired. I know that this diſtinction will aſtonish you at the firſt ſight, as it did terrifie me the firſt time that it ſounded in my eares: but our maiſters the Doctours haue farr more ſubtile diſtinctions which would deuide the very atomes. They ſay that he may be in perfection or perfect, that is not in the ſtate of perfection, and that ſome are in the ſtate of perfection which are farr from being in perfection or perfect.
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:178129:55"/> And that it is ſo, wee ſee but too many Monks, Religious men, &amp; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours of very ſcandalous and badd liues who are neuertheleſſe in the ſtate of perfection, and many lay men of very holy conuerſation, and moſt compleat in their owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, &amp; as it were perfect in their oeconomie, who are not for all that in the ſtate of perfection; yet our Doctours after many debats do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that it is farr better to be in perfection without the ſtate, then in the ſtate without perfection: Which do much comfort the ſimpler ſort who goe more round to worke, and preferr their ſaluation to their repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; in ſort that it is much better at all aduentures to be in the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his eſtate, then in the ſtate of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hauing nothing more ſure in all that matter then to ſearche his perfection in his owne profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and to liue in peace according the Counſell of the Apoſtle. This makes me think of thoſe Polititians,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:178129:56"/> who ſeing themſelues balanced betwixt reaſons of ſtate, and the conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Religion, as it were betweene the tree and the barke, do leaue ſometimes to ſupport Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; run to ſuccour the ſtate; or els they let the ſtate perish to conſerue Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, whenas they should main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <note place="margin">Pollicie &amp; Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion are the tvvo poles of all vvell gouerned common vvealthes</note> the one and the other if it were poſſible, as being the two poles, &amp; the two hinges of all well ordered common wealthes, giuing to Ceſar what belongs to Ceſar, and to God what belongs to God. Euen ſo amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teſtations, ſometimes a man doth quit the perfection of his eſtate to run to the ſtate of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he doth not care for the ſtate of perfection to aſpire to the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his eſtate: but it happens often to ſuch bad Polititians, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to conſerue the ſtate at the coſt &amp; chardges of Religion, that they looſe the one &amp; the other, as it doth happen to vnskilfull Pilotes vvho, to preſerue their shipp and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:178129:56"/> do make shipwrake of both together: thoſe that omitt to perfect themſelues in a laicall ſtate thinking to aduaunce themſelues more in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things in a Religious ſtate, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipating their atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions, do not proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in the one nor in the other, like <note place="margin">Romain Senatour</note> vnto that Romain Senatour, who being a very good man in his chardge of Senatour, did beleeue that in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king himſelf à Monke he would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an Angell, but he had ſuch bad ſucceſſe in the Monaſticall exerciſes, that his Abbot one day ſaid vnto him: My frend you left of to be a good Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natour <note place="margin">Many that are good in the vvorld may be badd in Religion.</note> to make a badd Monke. An example which makes me remember an other very remarkable which is rehearſed in the life of ſainct Philipp Nerio fundator of the Oratorians of Rome; he brought vp a yong Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Prieſt, called Francis Baſſus, who remayning for certaine yeeres vnder his diſcipline became a great prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, and full of rare qualities; at length a temptation ſurpriſed his
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:178129:57"/> thought, perſwading him that being but of the Oratorie, which is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of reformed Prieſts, who haue no other vowes, but ſuch as the Church annexed to Prieſthoode, that he was not in a ſtate of ſo great perfection, as if he had made himſelf a Monke in one of the begging Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Notwithſtanding any exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that S. Philipp made vnto him he yealded ſo much to this impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that he neuer ceaſed to purſue his pourpoſe till ſuch time as he was admitted to the Dominicans. Sainct Philipp did aſſiſt at his reception, &amp; at his profeſſion, &amp; albeit the Friars did think to haue purchaſed a great deale of honour to their Order, by the organe of a ſubiect which ſeemed to them ſo worthy of conſideration, yet the good Father, who loued him tenderlie, did nothing els but weepe during the ſolemnitie of theſe actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; and wheras the Dominica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s thought that it was becauſe he loſt one of the moſt famous worke men of his vigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard:
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:178129:57"/> Ha! ſaith he, it is not that, for charitie is not iealous, nor ſubiect to it owne proper intreſt, I deplore only the euident loſſe of ſo many vertus. He was a Prophet, for he that was ſo prudent, &amp; of ſo good edification in a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation, in which he did not beleeue to be in the ſtate of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be acquired, much leſſe acquired, did committ ſo many ſcandalls after in the Regularitie, that he gaue much paine and diſcontent to his Order. It is not alwaies the beſt to aſpire to the ſublimeſt degrees, the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous trades are thoſe that are exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in eminent places; the higher the aſcenſion be the heauier is the fall. You muſt not looke to be emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent wiſe, ſaith the holy word, but keepe your ſelf in an humble feare: <hi>Do not affect ſublimitie,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>but accommodate your ſelf to the litle ones.</hi> Let vs remember Iacob, who whould not haſten to goe with Eſaü, nor goe with a great pace towards his Fathers houſe, but
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:178129:58"/> chooſed rather to goe ſoft &amp; faire after his children &amp; his lambs, meanely, but ſurely.</p>
            <p>I do not intend by this diſcours to diuert any man from embracing the Regular life, contrarywiſe I do counſell it as much as I may, as did the great Apoſtle counſell chaſtitie, wishing that all had beene Virgins like himſelf. I know with what ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themes they are threatned that diuert faithfull people from theſe pathes of peace, &amp; from the way of <note place="margin">It is not lavv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to diſſvvade any from Religion.</note> the croſſe, and that it is in this point moſt of any other. that the Talion law should be executed with rigour, rendring to God in himſelf ſeruant for ſeruant, &amp; ſoule for ſoule. Alſo I know it is of this ſtate of life that it is ſaid, whoſoeuer can embrace it let him take it; yea, that it is good to preſſe ſweetly, without conſtraint, ſuch as be doubtfull and ſtaggring to put themſelues in it, to ſee &amp; taſt how ſweet our Lord is. It is good I ſay to giue them courage to lift them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:178129:58"/> vp vpon this ſacred Palme, to gather of it fruict: for no man can denie without offending our holy faith, &amp; the diſcipline of the Church, that which S. Ambroiſe ſaid here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore of voiled Virgins, ſuch as are now our Nuns, but it should and may be alſo ſaid of the Regulars, that they are a famous portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the flocke of IESVS CHRIST. That which is to be deſired in all this matter, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording my iudgment, (which is but a ſmall thing) is, that ſuch as are in this ſtate of perfection, either to be acquired as are the Regulars, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, as are the Paſtours, do not looke diſdainefullie, and as it were ouer the shoulders on thoſe that are at their feete, no more then doth the horſe troups of an armie deſpiſe the foote companies, becauſe that <note place="margin">Euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his ovvne profeſſion may vvork his ſaluation</note> theſe foote men, I would ſay theſe whoſe ſecular condition doth not oblige them to ſo great points of perfection, may make themſelues perfect and agreeable to God in
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:178129:59"/> their owne profeſſion. And recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, it is not fitt that ſuch as are not in the ſtate of perfection do inſolent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looſe the reſpect which is due to thoſe that dedicated themſelues to God by holy motions, and by the profeſſion of a life ſequeſtred from the world. This is neere the opinion of that great Apoſtle, who would not haue him that faſtes to deſpiſe him that eates nor tax him of gluttony, much leſſe would he haue him that eates mock him that faſtes, and reproach him of hypocriſie. And albeit thoſe that lead a chaſte life are in an eminent condition, as ſaith the holy word, that continence cannot be duely prized: Yet is the ſtate of marriage holy &amp; bleſſed by God, &amp; therfore ought to be reſpected, by Virgins themſelues. It is good for a man to humble himſelf in all things, ſaith the holy Ghoſt, and not to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire to things which are too great, or too ſublime. They muſt be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored that are in the ſtate of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:178129:59"/> but thoſe that are in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of their eſtate, do merit farr greater commendation, according that which the Apoſtle ſaith, that <note place="margin">Good Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours are vvorthy of double honour.</note> thoſe who in the Paſtorall chardge haue learning ioyned to good life, are worthie of double honour: for to that honour which is due to their qualitie should be ioyned that which is due to their proper merit.</p>
            <p>All thoſe faire conſiderations, ſaith Triſtan, do not ſatiſfie my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, which is to know in what doth conſiſt properlie this ſtate of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction acquired, or to be acquired. That I may not lye vnto you, quoth the Hermite, I am ſo badd a ſchola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Diuine, that thoſe very termes, which are not ſo well knowne to me as they are to ſuch as haue them euery day in their mouthes, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute hard of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon the Bench, do ſeeme very ſauage &amp; ſtrange to me. This word of perfection attributed to men doth aſtonish me, conſidering that the very Angels, which are in
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:178129:60"/> the ſtate of ſubſiſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce do not attribute it to themſelues but turne their wings ouer their eyes before the throne of God, who is only good and perfect, without euell and without fault. But that I do not blame, or it may be blaſpheme that which I do not well vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, without cenſuring the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours, or authoriſing the cenſurers of a Doctrine wherof I vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo litle, that the ſame litle is nothing; (if none vpon earthe be without ſpott, not a child of one day, ſaith the ſacred Texte; if the ſtarrs be not nete before him, who found diſorder amongſt his Angels) who can iuſtly alleage that he is in the ſtate of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, conſidering that to be perfect &amp; to be iuſt is the ſame thing, and that no man liuing can iuſtifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf before God? There is a certaine generation, ſaith the holy Ghoſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 30. <hi>v.</hi> 12.</note> which ſeeme to it ſelf, cleane &amp; yet is not washed from their fithlyneſſe: I know not which it is, but whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it be, we may compare it to the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:178129:60" rendition="simple:additions"/> Peacocke which atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo much to the looking glaſſe of her round taile, that shee forgetts the deformitie of her feete. Thoſe kind of people putts me in minde of that ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Hermite who imagined that he was an Angell, &amp; ſo <note place="margin">The ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of an ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Hermite.</note> threw himſelf into a well wherin he had died miſerablie if his fellowes had not drawen him out, and cured him of his follie. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, that I may not take the firebrand where it burnes, I will tell you my opinion with the ſimplicitie of a poore Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke, who knowes better how to make Images then to decide a point of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie: I do think that the Regulars do ſay they are in the ſtate of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to be acquired, in as much as they haue chooſen the Euangelicall Counſells as the shorteſt way to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riue to perfection, or els, be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Vvhy are Regulars ſaid to be in the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to be acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and Prelats in the ſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</note> there ſtate doth oblige the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſearche for that perfection which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed vnto them by their Rules, which is, as it were, the creame of the Euangelicall Doctrine: in ſort that
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:178129:61"/> their life should be nothing els but a perpetuall combat, a ſtudie &amp; exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe that aime at the acquiſition of perfection. And they ſay that the Prelats &amp; Paſtours are in the ſtate of perfection acquired, becauſe they are in eminent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions, whervnto none should be called but men conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated in Vertue &amp; ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: Or els be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are the ſucceſſours of the Apoſtles whom wee may not doubt <note place="margin">Prelats the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours of the Apoſtles.</note> to haue beene both very perfect, as being confirmed in grace, and alſo in the ſtate of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: or otherwiſe becauſe they are obliged by the greatneſſe of their dignitie, to be a patterne to the flock which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them, by their good exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple: or alſo becauſe they ought in this ſtate, to exerciſe not ſimple &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon vertus; out heroicall and important vertus, wherof the greateſt according the iudgment of the Goſpell, is to giue his owne ſoule for the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his flock. This was alſo the Rule by which our Sauiour meaſured the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:178129:61"/> of ſainct Peter, before making <note place="margin">No chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie goes beyond that of the Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall charg<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> him his Lieutenant in earthe, when he demaunded of him three times if he did loue him more then the reſt, &amp; that to his affirmatiue anſweares CHRIST replied; <hi>feede then my sheepe,</hi> finding no greater proofe of loue then the exerciſe of this Paſtorall charge.</p>
            <p>If Monaſtical and Conuentuall perſons, quoth Triſtan be not in the ſtate of perfection to be acquired but in reſpect of the obligation which they haue to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues perfect, &amp; that the Prelats are not in the ſtate of perfection acquired, but becauſe they are obliged to be exemplar, me thinks the ſtate of all Chriſtians in generall is ſuch, conſidering that our Sauiour in the Ghoſpell ſaid vnto vs: <hi>Be perfect as your Celeſtiall father is, vvho doth make his ſunne shine equallie vpon the good and vpon the bad, and povvre his raine vvithout distinction vpon the land of the iuſt and the iniuſt.</hi> And what? Kings &amp; Pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſtes, who
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:178129:62"/> as Conſtantin the great ſaid, are the exterior Bishops, Magiſtrats, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of houſes, and all thoſe that are in ſublimitie and Superioritie, are not they bound to giue good example to their inferiours, and to be a good odour to all men in IESVS CHRIST? After this manner they shall be in the ſtate of the perfection of Prelats, who are the Princes within the Church. And all Chriſtians that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to come to the perfection of their eſtate shall not they, by this deſire, as well as by vowes be in the ſtate of perfection to be acquired, as well as the Regulars?</p>
            <p>I would be neere of your opinion in that, quoth the Hermite, if I did not feare to offend our Maiſters the Doctours, who haue in their hands the kees of the doctrine, who doe open that which no man durſt shut, who doe shutt that which no man durſt open, and who haue, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of ſcience. But the reſpect which I beare to their opinions, which to
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:178129:62"/> me are Oracles, to which I ſubmitt my owne iudgment, do make me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce to my owne particular reaſon; and follow the moſt common opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, conſidering that the Apoſtle doe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidd vs all contentions. But yet when I conſider with my ſelfe that the <note place="margin">The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels vvere at varia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce ſor the body of Moyſes.</note> Angels of heauen were at veriance betweene themſelues for the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the body of Moyſes, I doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that men conſecrated to God, either by the Sacerdotall character, or by the Monaſticall habit, who are called in the Scripture the Angells of the God of armies, may a litle conteſt about the ſtate of perfection, euery one being glad, without preiudice to humilitie and charitie, to magnifie his owne miniſterie, according the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the diuine Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>Paſſe for magnifying their miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but to deſpiſe others and to pull from thoſe who according God &amp; man do both appeere, and are in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect more worthy then they; that is the thing which I cannot approuue,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:178129:63"/> quoth Triſtan, for had you knowne how the Conuentuall Friars did deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiffer vnto me the Eccleſiaſticall Clergie whom they call Seculars; how they did depreſſe this condition, &amp; repreſent it vnto me not only to be baſe but alſoe dangerous, and aboue all the reſt, how they did teare in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the condition of you Hermites, I beleeue that had you had the patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Iob you would breake out in cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler againſt them.</p>
            <p>For why should they take from the Paſtours, Prieſts, Pteachers, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours, Confeſſours, Vicars, Chano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Deanes, Abbots, and Priours called Commendataries, &amp; from you Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites the pretention to the ſtate of perfection to be acquired? Sir, quoth Nicephorus, I did wind my ſelfe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly about this ſubiect without en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into it, to shun this rock againſt which you force me now to ſtrick, all that I can doe is, to ſay with S. Paul, that you conſtraine me to paſſe through this danger and exceede a
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:178129:63"/> litle the limits of moderation: <hi>Be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie,</hi> quoth the Pſalmiſt or according an other verſion: <hi>Stirr and frett a litle, but do not ſinne.</hi> Vnder this permiſſion <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.</note> I vvill ſay to God: <hi>Lord put a ſentinell to my mouth, and a doore of circumſtances to my lipps, to the end that my tongue may not vtter vvords of precipitation, or of mallice.</hi> I know it is vvritten, <hi>thou shalt not ſpeake ill of the Gods:</hi> That is to ſay, of eminent perſons, either in qualitie or ſanctitie, becauſe that greatnes and pietie doe make men approche to the Diuinitie. But albeit Socrates and Plato are my frends, and that I doe perfectlie honour the Regular Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, yet the zeale of the truthe hath more power ouer me then all that. I will then ſay this word of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, not for my ſelf who am the meaneſt of all men, &amp; the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible (a title which one of the Prophets gaue to our Sauiour) but for ſoe many graue and venerable Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall perſons which are in the ranke of the Clergie, and compoſe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:178129:64"/> the true Hierarchie of the Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted <note place="margin">Vvho are of the Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie.</note> by IESVS CHRIST, and whoſe miſſion &amp; vocation is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diuine, that it is to pull away the faireſt roſe of the crowne of ſoe many ſacred Prieſts, to take from them the honour to be in the ſtate of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, at leaſtwiſe to be acquired, in which the Regulars doe not ſtick to put their ſeruants, &amp; the verie Nuns, as well thoſe that ſing in the Quire, as their maids ſeruants that looke to the buſineſſe of the Conuent. Ah! where shall Prieſtly vnctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be placed, which make thoſe that are adorned with it a holy and Royall people, if they make the ſtate of it inferiour to the ſtate of a ſimple girle, who hath commaund to hold her peace, and no right to ſpeake within the Church, or to ſome porter or garde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Conuent? Thoſe that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche to the Altar, to whoſe words God doth make himſelf obedient, who haue the kees of the kingdome <note place="margin">The fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and povver of a Prieſt orderly laid dovvne.</note> of heauen, who doe bind and looſe,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:178129:64"/> who are the Magiſtrats of the Church, who ſitt vpon the ſeate of iudgment in the houſe of Dauid, and iudge the twelue tribs of Iſraël, that is to ſay, all the world; whoſe ſentences giuen vpon earth are confirmed and rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in heauen, whoſe hands bleſſed and conſecrated doe handle the moſt dreadfull myſteries of our Religion, and who do that thing which the Angells do adore; who haue power ouer the Diuels, who diſpence the Sacraments, and confer the grace of God to all mortall men; thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine men which S. Francis preferred <note place="margin">S. <hi>Francis prefered Prieſts to the very Angels.</hi>
               </note> to the Angels, becauſe that one only man of them doth make euery day that which all the Angels in heauen cannot doe. For to whom of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels was it euer ſaid, conſecrate my body, and what thou shalt looſe on earth shall be looſed in heauen? thoſe men that are almoſt to be adored, &amp; that the Angells do reuerence and call their fellow ſeruants to God, shall they be the vnderlings of thoſe
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:178129:65"/> which doe not merit (in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their dignitie) to looſe the lachets of their shooes? Ah! Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulars, pardon me, it is the zeale of the houſe of God which doth gnaw me, it is the deſire of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and of his beautie which I ſee dried vp in his principall members, which doth tranſport me to tell you, that you vſe very diſcourteouſly your elders the Eccleſiaſticall Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, whom (forſooth) you call Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, notwithſtanding that by their Clericall habit they haue depoſed <note place="margin">Secular is no fitt Epitetho for a prieſt.</note> the ignominie of the ſecular habit, &amp; that by the reception of their holy Orders they haue renounced to the deſires of the world, and to all that is profane in it. It ſeemes that you would imitate Iacob, and ſupplant them as if they were all Eſaüs, but know; that if you be Hebrewes, ſo are they; if you be Iſraëlites, ſo are they; if you be the ſeede of Abraham, ſo are they; and I will ſay more for them, that they are both more an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:178129:65"/> in the Church, and of a greater ranke (witneſſe the proceſſions) &amp; of a higher dignitie, &amp; of more emine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t functions, I will ſay ſo much (for it <note place="margin">The Church may be vvithout Monks but not vvithout Paſtours.</note> is no time for a man to hold himſelf vp when he is shaked and falling downe) that their imployments are more vtile and more neceſſarie then yours, for the Church hath beene &amp; may be without Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks, but it cannot be without Paſtours, without Vicars, without Prieſts, without Doctours, without Preachers: for if the ſalt be molte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with what shall men ſalt? if the candle be quinched how shall men haue light? Perchance you will ſay that you doe the ſame actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which <note place="margin">It doth not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Regulars to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> the Paſtours doe, but in you it is but in way of acceſſarie, in them princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally; in you it is pleaſure, in them paine; in you it is of free will, in them of neceſſitie; in you by way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, and as paſſingers, in them it is of dutie and office; in you it is without chardge of ſoules, in them with chardge, which make them to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:178129:66"/> be anſwerable for the ſoules, and ſo farr anſwerable that they shall giue ſoule for ſoule, and bloud for bloud; in you it is but in ſome things, in them in all things; in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at all times, in you when you pleaſe, &amp; that your commoditie doth permit it; in you ſo that the ſeruice of your commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie doth marche before that of the neighbour, in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is no excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; in you it is at certaine houres, in them at all moments; you fight as voluntaries, they as neceſſaries; you marche but in the wings of the battle, they make the body of the armie; they carrie the waight of the heate of the day, and the cold of the dew of the night, in ſummer and in winter, in ſpring time and in harueſt, without rule in their dyet, without aſſurance in their ſleepe. Of ſeuen Sacraments you adminiſter but two, and the one of them which is the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, but at your eaſe, within your houſes, without carrying it to the ſick in the heate of the ſunne, in
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:178129:66"/> froſt, in ſnow, in raine and in <note place="margin">Th life and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of poore Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed.</note> tempeſt, at all houres of the day &amp; of the night, and all dayes of the yeere through the dirt &amp; inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the cities and townes, through the woods and the meere, through the mountaines and the vallees, through the ſtones and the moores of the fields. And the other Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is that of pennance you adminiſter, when you are prayed, &amp; particularly called vpon, and as pleaſeth your Superiours, who haue as great care of the conſeruation of their owne ſubiects, as they haue of the ſick, for whom they are not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable. But the Paſtours by obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation ought to keepe ſtill neere the ſick, to preſſe them to enter in fauour with God by the Sacrament of reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, to preache vnto them in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, to the end to make them think of their ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is part of their owne ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, as being bound to giue account to the Prince of Paſtours
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:178129:67"/> the Bishop of our ſoules IESVS CHRIST, of his sheepe committed to their Vigilance. As for Marriage, Baptiſme &amp; Extreme-Vnction, they are things which you do not medle with all (they are for the gleaners) no more then you medle with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Order which you leaue for the Bishops. This you shew your prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; declare that you haue eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both butter and honny, which make you reiect the leaſt and chooſe the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaia</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 15.</note> beſt, &amp; that you know how to make vſe hanſomely of the fanne which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate the corne from the chaffe, and pretious things from vile and baſe things. You doe not ſnuff your lamps but with golden ſnuffers, &amp; you doe not take the coales as the Seraphim of the Prophet, but with gilt tongs. The rodd of Moyſes doth not pleaſe you, becauſe ſometimes it is turned to a ſerpent and deuoure, or doth worke dreadfull and rude effects: The rodd of Aaron fitts you beſt, becauſe it ingenders nothing but
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:178129:67"/> flowres &amp; fruict. Euen ſo you know <note place="margin">Friars ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the profit &amp; leaue the paine for the prieſts</note> how to pull the roſe without tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the thornes, to gather the hony without feeling the ſting of the bee, to eate the kernell of the nutt &amp; caſt away the shell, &amp; to doe as children doe when they gett bread &amp; butter, licke away the butter and leaue the breade. To cooperate to the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſoules without taking chardge of them, is properly to take away the creame and leaue the curd. It is an admirable thing to ſee that ſuch as gouerne the people will not take chardge of them, and ſuch as haue chardge of them and are anſwerable for them, cannot haue the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them. And with all theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licatneſſe &amp; ſpirituall allurements, they are in the ſtate of perfection, and thoſe who like Gyants do grone vnder the waters, that is to ſay, vnder the chardge of the people, who are the waters of the ſea of the world, shall be out of perfection? Truely I am faithfull, and beleeue all that the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:178129:68"/> Church doth beleeue, and if the Church beleeue that, I beleeue it alſo, but not without captiuating my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to the obedience of faith.</p>
            <p>Would not you thinke that thoſe good people vould faine add a cubite more to their ſtature, or to ſpeake otherwiſe, would faine extoll their owne eſtate putting betwixt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; the Paſtours inferours to Prelats, their lay brothers? For if thoſe be in the ſtate of perfection, and not the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, Paſtours and other Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call perſons of the Clergie, to what height do they raiſe themſelues, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their ſeruants and their cookes before thoſe that are the Maiſters, the Fathers, and the Doctours of the people? What? and if they preferr to them ſimple vailed girles, yea the lay ſiſters, is it not to deſtroy the law of nature, and the gouernement of the Church, which in all kind of fashion hath declared women kind inferiour to men? If the iniquitie of a man is
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:178129:68"/> preferred to the well doing of a woman, what good can a woman do, ſuppoſe shee made miracles, which may be compared to the greatneſſe of Prieſthoode? Would not men laugh at the impertine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of him that would giue the title of Excellence to a poore man that asketh almes from doore to doore, &amp; would but thou a ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle man of note, or a Magiſtrate. The Regulars, and principally the begging Orders haue baggs which ſpeake dayly for them asking almes, and yet they muſt haue ſo many Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternities and ſo many Reuerences giuen them; and the Paſtours and Prieſts shall be without honour, and vnworthelie treated ſo farr forth as <note place="margin">Great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities.</note> to be putt in a ranke and ſtate in the Church, more low then that of the Friar ſeruants of the Reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. But yet amongſt themſelues they know well how to keep the beſt place for Prieſthoode, and keepe the Conuers or lay Brothers in the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie and baſeneſſe of ſeruitude, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguishing
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:178129:69"/> themſelues by theſe ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes Fathers and Brothers, albeit all of them are Brothers and children of one Order &amp; of one habit, making profeſſion of one and the ſelf ſame rule, liuing vnder the ſame obſeruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and the ſame vowes, &amp; all of them as well prieſts as others not permitted heretofore to take any other title but that of Brother, which is well obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the moſt humble and moſt <note place="margin">Friars he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retofore had no other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion but that of Brother.</note> moderate of them. And I pray you, is prieſthoode another thing in the Regulars the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is in the Clergie? Is it an other charracter, an other Order, an other power, for being vnder a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puce, vnder ſandales, vnder a ſcapu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, or vnder a claſpe? Is it more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſo then vnder a ſurplice, vnder a ſutane, and vnder a corner capp? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes we are now come to the time wherin the laſt are the firſt, and the firſt are put in the laſt ranke. In your opinion to plant cabbage, to washe disheſſe, to carrie a bag, to keepe a doore, to ſnuff lamps, to patch, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:178129:69"/> the ordinarie exerciſe of the lay brothers of the Conuents, are they employments comparable to that of the Paſtours, who do conſecrate the <note place="margin">The fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Paſtours.</note> body of the ſonne of God, who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence the merits of his bloud in the Sacrament of pennance, who do bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, who do annoinct the ſick, who do marrie thoſe that are called to that holy yoake, and do ſuch other Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall functions?</p>
            <p>Verely, quoth Triſtan, you reſtore them well what they lent you, and their bill of exchange is well payed in the ſame coyne. If I had not knowne that you are well verſed in theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in controuerſie, I would ſay that you are a Prophet, and that you haue heard part of that which they ſaid to me, to diuert me from being an Hermite, or of the ſecular Clergie, ſo well you rehearſe the particularities of that which they inſinuated to me. For me thought I heard them ſay, that all deuotions co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to Religious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion is but orpin co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to gold, &amp;
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:178129:70"/> glaſſe compared to a diamant, &amp; that they are like to thoſe Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcarlets, which ſeemed all ſtayned and deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lored, when they were put neere that piece of purple of Tyr and Sidon, which for the excellencie of it was <note place="margin">The fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Regulars inferiour to that of Prieſts &amp; Paſtours.</note> ſent to the Emperour. For ought I ſee then their ſtate of perfection doth not proceede from their functions, which are inferiour in greatneſſe, in eminencie, in vtilitie, in neceſſitie to that of Prieſts and Paſtours, but from their vowes; it is ſo held commonly in the ſchooles, quoth the Hermite, <note place="margin">Schoole diuinitie diſputes of all matters, &amp; moues as many queſtions as it doth decide.</note> but ſeing this ſort of Theologie doth maintaine as much diſpute and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie as it doth decide, &amp; ſtirrr vp as much as it doth reſolue, no point of faith ſo ſacred on which she doth not moue queſtions and frame diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties; of this point which is but of gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, I think that without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending Religion, wee may ſpeake problematically, ſubmitting alwaies moſt humblie &amp; moſt abſolutely our particular reaſon &amp; iudgment to the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:178129:70"/> iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the vniuerſall Church, &amp; to the holy ſea Apoſtolike, the firme &amp; fundamentall ſtone, againſt which errours, which are the gates of hell, may not preuaile. I ſay then after this proteſtation, which may ſerue me as a buckler againſt the plotts of calumnie, that if the ſtate of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to be acquired doth conſiſt in vowes, the Prieſts of the Clergie, who are in the Hierarchie of the Church, ought to be admitted to it: For they make two ſolemne and indiſpenſable <note place="margin">Prieſts make tvvo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne vovves.</note> vowes of chaſtitie and obedience, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to their holy Orders. And if they do not make the vow of poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, it is becauſe that being not in Commonaltie, as the Regulars are, but as the Apoſtles were, diſperſed <note place="margin">Prieſts diſperſed amongſt the people do imit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat the Apoſtles.</note> amongſt the people as the ſalt of the earth, it would be impoſſible for them to obſerue it in that manner that the Conuentualls do. But if it pleaſed them to goe to the Countrie, and to ſee in the villages to what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie of neceſſitie are the poore
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:178129:71"/> Paſtours brought, they would haue occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſay that it is much eaſier to vow pouertie, as the Regulars doe, then to practiſe it as the Paſtours do. The Regulars cannot ſing but in very cloſe Quires, they cannot ſay Maſſe <note place="margin">The plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t life of Regulars in theſe Countries</note> but with ſiluer challices, with nete veſtments &amp; with parfums, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſleepe but in hoate celles, they cannot eate but very nete meate, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per &amp; well ſeaſoned, in gilt and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Refectories, accompanied with pleaſant lecture, hauing after euery refection a full houre of recreation, they cannot walke but in faire gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s all laced with flowers &amp; arrouſed with fontaines, they cannot goe but vnder Cloiſters &amp; well couered from ſunne &amp; raine, they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not make their aſſemblies but in Chapters well po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished and very lightſome, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtudy but in faire and ample Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliothekes, in ſomme he that would learne a thouſand litle ſecrets for the commoditie of mans liuing, let him take the paines to conſider the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſticall
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:178129:71"/> &amp; Conue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuall life. Inſteede that the Paſtours of the Countrey <note place="margin">The life of a Country Paſtour.</note> (for thoſe of the citie are a litle better prouided, but yet are they alſo in trouble ouer head &amp; shoulders) are loged in cabanes, like the grott of Bethleem, expoſed at all times to the iniurie of the aire, they lie vpon the ſtraw and vpon the ground, they are nourished like clownes, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, without conſolation, they haue much paine and litle Vnction, they are ill loged, ill attired, ill payed, ill aſſiſted, miſerable in their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, in their orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, in their load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, in their houshould-ſtuffs, &amp; in all other things. And for all this, the Regulars amiddeſt all commodities <note place="margin">Prieſts held to be riche though othervvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe more poore the Friars.</note> haue the glorie of the ſtate of pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the Paſtours in all neceſſities and want are held for riche, &amp; to be diſpoſſeſſed of the ſtate of perfection, which properlie doth not conſiſt ſo much in the vow of pouertie, as wee ſaid before, as it doth in the practiſe of voluntarie, &amp; Euangelicall pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:178129:72"/> which is when a man ſelling all that he hath doth giue it to the poore, without aſſurance of any prop or the help of any commonaltie, of which wee ſee very few exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples. For, to forſake thirtie or fiftie pound rent to caſt himſelf into a Monaſterie that hath a thouſand pound rent, and to haue his part of the ſame with thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or fortie other Monks, I do not ſee that ſuch a leape is any thing dangerous: but to leaue great reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes in the world &amp; diſtribute them to the needie to put himſelf all alone, &amp; without ayde in a naked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicitie, as did the Apoſtles, who reſerued nothing of all the goods which the firſt Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s brought &amp; laid at their feete, is a practiſe that is as rare as it is excellent, &amp; ſome Regulars might be found which would call it temeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, although it be the true manner of the pouertie counſelled in the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, in which our Sauiour, who did counſell it, did place perfection. But let vs make this matter agree, a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:178129:72"/> man that is proprietaire shall be deepelie in imperfection, becauſe he doth contrarie to his vow, and yet in vertue of the ſame vow, he shall be ſaid to be in the ſtate of perfection: <note place="margin">It is not all one to be in the ſtate of per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fection &amp; to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</note> and a ſecular ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who doth diſtribute all his goods in almes to follow our Sauiour, by this renouncement of his goods shall be without doubt well aduanced in perfection, and yet shall not he be in the ſtate of perfection? For my part I muſt acknowledge at one time both my ignorance, and the groſeneſſe of my vnderſtanding, that cannot get out the connection, of this admirable diſtinction, which me thinks cannot ſubſiſt but by this, <hi>eſſe rationale,</hi> wherof there is ſuch great debate betweene the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, and by ſeparating by the thought the ſtate of perfection, as they ſeparate in man, the animal part from the reaſonnable. But perchance I shall expound my ſelf better by this example.</p>
            <p>A good Paſtour of a village, who <note place="margin">An exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of a poore Paſtour.</note>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:178129:73"/> was (as almoſt all of them be) in the perfection of pouertie in his owne eſtat, receiued to his poore cabane a Conuentuall Friar, that should be a foote by his rule, but in effect was well mounted he entertayned him accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the short exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of his power &amp; of his meanes. Wodden &amp; earthen disheſſe were his beſt mouables, new ſtraw was his beſt bedd, the ground was his moſt aſſured bedſtead, two brones made his fire, and the middeſt of the place was his cheminie, a block was his chaire, his table was two pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks ill ioinct together, held vp by ſome ſticks made in forme of a treſtle, ill faſtned; for the reſt he was ſo auſtere that ſcarce he did weare any lynnen: he found neuertheleſſe ſome napkin; for the vſe of table-cloathes were as much vnknowne to him, as they are to the Capucins. The Religious ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who had occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eſteeme more of his good reception then of his good cheere, and of the Paſtours good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will then of the effects of it, drew
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:178129:73"/> a purſe out of his ſleeue, well fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished with a kind of mettall which is the rule and meaſure of all things, yet forbidden in the rule of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentuall Friars; With this he thought to entertaine himſelf in all places: but this village was as ill furnished with things neceſſarie, as was the houſe of the good Paſtour. He was therfore conſtrayned to content himſelf with a kind of pottage and ſome pulſe, but to take this leane refection he vſed many fashions, &amp; diſpoſed himſelfe with much delicatneſſe and proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; he drew from his pocket a caſe wherin there was a ſiluer ſpoone, a forke of the ſame mettall, &amp; a knife with a haft alſo of ſiluer. The good Paſtour who had a pleaſant witt, and knew a litle more then his Proſne or ſonday Sermons ſeing this Regular ſumptuoſitie ſaid to the friar, Father, you and I would make one good Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke, for you would make the vow of pouertie, and I would keepe it. This blow of the beck or mouth did
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:178129:74"/> not hinder the good Friars teeth, who did not looſe a whitt of his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petit for it. Now tell me, I pray you, who before God had the merit of pouertie, he that was really poore, and vſed hoſpitalitie, or he that was not poore but in vow, with ſo much delicatneſſe? For my part, quoth Triſtan, I beleeue that as he is much commended in the Scripture that might tranſgreſſe, and do euell, &amp; did it not: Euen ſo he, that putting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the ſtate of perfection, &amp; doth not tend to it, but lett himſelf fall into imperfections, shall be whipt with many ſtripes. And as the merits of Regulars, are very great whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they do their dutie well, ſo are their faults very notable when they faile therin. They are like the figgs of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, either all good, or all badd, which makes me remember an other example.</p>
            <p>A man of qualitie that liued very <note place="margin">An exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of a man of quality &amp; of his ſeruant.</note> diſſolute, being touched with repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of his ſinnes did caſt himſelfe
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:178129:74"/> into a Monaſterie: and a ſeruant of his much fearing God following him in that retrait of the world, was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the ſame Monaſterie in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of a lay brother. What hapned? the Maiſter that knew his owne ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and that ſaw without ceaſe his ſinnes before his eyes, became ſo humble by that conſideration, that he became a good Religious man, &amp; the ſeruant contrarywiſe ſeing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf entred into the portion of Saints in a good riche Monaſterie, became ſo inſolent &amp; ſo delicate that nothing could content his vanitie and delicat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: He that was his Maiſter in the world ſeruing him with all ſort of charitie and cordialitie he did checke and rebuke him like a ſlaue; which the other did indure with incredible patience, by which he gayned heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the ſeruant became ſo arrogant and ſo preſumptuous, that in the end his ſottiſneſſe and diſorder did oblige the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monaltie to take the habit fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his back and chaſe him away ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſlie
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:178129:75"/> like a knawe, that became as inſupportable as he was incorrigible. Euen ſo the ſame ſunne which melt wax, doth harden dirt, &amp; Regularitie which is inſtituted as a holy Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, to giude thoſe that put themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in it, as becommeth, to perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was cauſe of the imperfection of this ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, who had done far better if he had remayned in his firſt ſtate of life. And indeede ſolitude, which the Scripture and experience doth teach vs to be ſo proper to draw to it the Spirit of God, is often cauſe of the ruine of ſuch as caſt themſelues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it without iudgment. Loth, that was ſo wiſe and ſo chaſte in an infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous citie infected with the moſt horrible diſorder that ſenſualitie could commit, became diſſolute and inceſtuous in the deſert. And ſome Regulars do ſay that they find none ſo tractable nor ſo humble as thoſe that were before eminent in dignitie in the world, nor none ſo arrogant &amp; harder to be gouerned then thoſe
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:178129:75"/> that coming from baſe deſcent, do ſee themſelues as the Aſſe of Iſis in the Embleme, honored becauſe of the reputation of ſainctitie which there <note place="margin">The Friars much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored by their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits.</note> habit doth gett vnto them, and that without it, neither by their birth, nor by their merits should they be any thing eſteemed. It is to thoſe that it belongs to ſay with the Pſalmiſt, my cordes or knots, that is to ſay, my vowes do me great honour, &amp; they are the moſt excellent portion of my inheritance. And if eaſe &amp; commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie doe carrie them to immodera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then may they ſay that their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie doth proceed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their fatneſſe and from the abondance of their breade, being no more ſubiect to the labour &amp; trauaile of other men. And if proprietie do ſlide amongſt them, then is all loſt, for that is the ſinne of Achan which draw malediction, vpon their heads.</p>
            <p>For ought I can gather out of your diſcours, quoth Triſtan, the ſtate of perfection acquired in which are all
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:178129:76"/> Prelats doth conſiſt in the eminencie of their dignitie &amp; character: and the ſtate of perfection to be acquired, wherin are the Regulars, doth conſiſt in their three vowes, in which they put the eſſence of Regularitie. That is the opinion of ſome Doctours, ſaith Nicephorus, but in this ſubiect all are not of the ſame opinion. And that it is ſo, the Regulars themſelues do make diſtinctions of the ſtate of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection amongſt them, and although their Prouincialls and Generalls who with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do hold the place of Bishops and Archbishops in their particular Hierarchie, are but ſimple Prieſts for <note place="margin">Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours of Regulars are but ſimple Prieſts.</note> their character, &amp; for theſe dignities vnknowne in the Church foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeeres agoe, neuertheleſſe do they repute them to be in the ſtate of perfection acquired as Prelats are, &amp; they giue them alſo the name of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats, which doth paſſe to the Abbots by they Titulars or Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendataries, and to many others in the Court of Rome, which haue no Prelatship but
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:178129:76"/> by name only, hauing no chardge of ſoules nor any functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Church. Some Regulars do make this ſtate of perfection acquired to deſcend yet more low, to their Priours, Gardiens, Miniſters, Correctours, Rectours &amp; other Superiours of particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uents, although they denie it to Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats &amp; Paſtours of Parisheſſe, it may be with as litle reaſon as they do at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute it to themſelues. For I do not think that I should ſwarue much fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the iudgment of the truthe and of the <note place="margin">Paſtours as great as the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours of Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> Church, if I should ſay that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours are at the leaſt as great &amp; grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the Superiours of Regular houſes, as hauing many more ſoules vnder their gouernement then they haue; for where is that Monaſterie which hath fortie or fiftie thouſand Friars in it, as there is a Parish that <note place="margin">S. Euſtaſe in Paris for one.</note> hath ſo many Pariſioners within it precinct, and which is more, holding <note place="margin">The Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie is the principall &amp; moſt ancient of the Church.</note> the ſame ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke in the firſt, principall &amp; moſt ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Hierarchie of the church, which is that of the Cleargie, that
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:178129:77"/> the Clauſtrall Priors and Superiours do hold in the ſecond and new Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie, of Regulars? There do not want alſo ſome famous Doctours <note place="margin">The Regu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lars ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke a nevv Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues.</note> which haue placed the Paſtours in the ſtate of perfection acquired; as the Prelats are, becauſe they haue the ſame obligation which they haue (&amp; in ſome ſort more ſtrict then they, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are the immediat Paſtours of the people that put their liues in hazard for the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their flock. For it is in that that the high point <note place="margin">Perfect charitie in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorall chardge.</note> of perfect charitie doth conſiſt, and conſequentlie the topp of acquired perfection. Wherfore then ſaith Triſtan, do they caſt you ſo farr of (I ſpeake of you Hermites) from the ſtate of perfection to be acquired? It is without doubt, becauſe you do not make the vowes nor the profeſſion of any rule. Sir, ſaid Nicephorus, I did alwaies diuert my ſelf from that blow, deſiring rather to ſpeake of thoſe that are of ſome worth in the Church the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vs poore ſolitarie people, who liue
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:178129:77"/> in obſcuritie, among the dead men of the world, of which there is no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Catalogue of the liuing: but ſeing you, by your inquiries do preſent them vpon the ſtage, who by the profeſſion of their life ought to hide the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, to imitate our Sauiour in his hidden life, it is requiſit that I ſpeake vnto you of a thing that is not, as of a thing that is. Know then that as there are Conuentuall friars and Conuentuall friars, ſo are there Hermites and Hermites. There <note place="margin">Good &amp; bad friars as there be good and bad Hermites</note> is not almoſt any Order of Regulars wherof there is not a Reformation, in ſort that ſuch as liue according the ſtrict obſeruance of their rule are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Reformed, and the others the Mitigate, a name truely too milde, which doth iniuſtly flatter their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order and relaxation. For mitigation doth preſuppoſe ſome temperature of auſteritie in the rule by Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall authoritie: But not ſo manifeſt infraction of the vowes of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and pouertie, as that which is
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:178129:78"/> knowne to be, and which the holy ſea did neuer authorize. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner there are Hermites vacabonds &amp; voluntaries, who haue neither houſe nor home, children of Belial, who will haue no yoke nor ſubiection, who liue after their owne fancie, and as the Pſalmiſt ſaith, who do walke in their owne deſires, &amp; paſſe their liues according the inconſtant affection of their harts: <hi>Cloudes vvithout vvater</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ep. Iudae.</note> 
               <hi>carried about of vvindes;</hi> and for whom the tempeſt of darkneſſe is reſerued, &amp; perpetuall vnquietneſſe in punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their inſtabilitie. Theſe kind of people are Hermites only by habit, &amp; not by life, by apparence and not by effect, people without approbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſlaues to their proper wills, and not only farr from the ſtate of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but alſo from the perfection of their eſtate, if a condition ſo vncertaine &amp; ſo irregular may be called an eſtate. But there are other Hermites, who are in the ſtabilitie of a ſetled life, true followers and children of thoſe
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:178129:78"/> firſt Anacorites, who like shining ſtarrs lightned the heauen of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church by the liuely beames of their holy vertues, whoſe memorie shall neuer perish, but will be ſtill co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued freshe, in the very decline of time, and in the old age of the world They are men that ſtick like Iuie to the ſtock &amp; wall of the Eccleſiaſticall Hierarchie and like the vigne that ioyne faſt to the elme tree. Thoſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do ſequeſter themſelues from the world by a locall ſolitude, to the end to harken more attentiuely in the mentall ſolitude that, which God shall ſpeake to their harts. They haue choſen the beſt part with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but in that ſort that when the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of the neighbour or the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the Church doth call them, they imitate theſe wiſe maydens, as ſaid that ancient Hermite, who neuer departed their fathers houſe, but to carrie water when their neighbours houſe was ſurpriſed with fier. Charitie &amp; neceſſitie being the only two cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:178129:79"/> which might and ought iuſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt the ſweet repoſe of their ſilence. Theſe Hermites are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutelie and entirelie ſubiect to the Ordinaries, who are the Bishops, they may be iudged by their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialls, they are ſubiect to the viſits of their Generall Vicars and Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, and they acknowledge alſo for their Superiours &amp; Paſtours, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours in whoſe Parisheſſe are ſituated their Hermitages. Theſe do receiue their holy habit at the hands of the Prelats, or of ſuch as are depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them to cloath them with the Eccleſiaſticall benedictions &amp; ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, they goe not out of the Dioceſe without leaue, they eſtablish themſelues in their dwellings with the permiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; leaue of the Bishops and Paſtours, &amp; alſo with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent <note place="margin">A good example for Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</note> of the neighbouring people, they do not begg but with the licence of the Paſtours; in ſomme they depend in all things of their wills. If they be Prieſts, they make the two ſolemne
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:178129:79"/> vowes annexed to holy orders, betwene the hands of the moſt Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Bishop who doth conſecrat them, which are the vowes of chaſtitie and obedience, and that they may not looſe alſo the merit of the vow of pouertie, beſids the practiſe which they make of it by begging, many of them do vow it betwene the hands of the Prelats or of their Officers, bereauing themſelues of all proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and reſeruing but the ſimple vſe of the almes which are giuen them, readie to quitt the ſame at the firſt command of thoſe whom the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hath giuen them for Superiours. What think, you Sir, are thoſe men in the ſtate of perfection to be acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as are the Conuentuall friars? I would think they are, quoth Triſtan, but the Conuentualls do not think it, who do not put the ſtate of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the vowes only, but do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire beſids that they be made vnder ſome of the Rules approued by the Church.</p>
            <pb n="146" facs="tcp:178129:80"/>
            <p> Truely, quoth the Hermite, that is extreme rigour; but I pray you, what better rule can wee haue then that of the Scripture, then the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Patriarches &amp; Prophets, who liued in the wilderneſſe, then that of our Sauiour faſting in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, transfiguring himſelfe vpon mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Thabor, and paſſing a great part of his life vpon the moſt retired moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines; then that of his fore-runner ſaint Iohn Baptiſt, then that of ſaint Paul the firſt Hermite, of great ſaint Anthonie, of ſaint Hilarion; in ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, of ſo many thouſand Anacore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, whoſe names writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the booke of life are glorious in heauen, and bleſſed on earthe? Can any man doubt but theſe excellent Anacore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes were in the ſtate of perfection although they did not make the three vowes vnder any rule? In good ſooth, a man muſt haue extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie patience to indure theſe inequali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and to ſpeake with the ſacred Amante; <hi>The children of my mother</hi>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:178129:80"/> 
               <hi>fought againſt me, &amp; put me, in the gard of the vignes.</hi> It did not appertaine but to S. Paul to diuulge his owne proper praiſes with good grace, becauſe he did know how to referr all very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to God, when he ſaid: <hi>Not I, but the grace of God in me, by vvhich I am that which I am: but I did menage it well, &amp; in ſuch ſort as it was not inutile in my hands.</hi> I dare neuertheleſſe praiſe my ſoule in God as ſaith the Pſalmiſt, to the end to reioice the curteous, and tell you, that if ſo be the Regulars do ſay they are themſelues in the ſtate of perfection, for hauing made the three vowes vnder a certaine Rule betwene the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of their Superiours, <note place="margin">The Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours of Regulars are but ſimple Prieſts.</note> who are but ſimple Prieſts, I think to haue right to ſay the ſame, hauing receiued my habit by the hands of a Bishop, made profeſſion of the ſame vowes betwene his hands, vnder ſuch rules &amp; Conſtitutions as pleaſed his charitie to preſcribe vnto me, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo ſubmitted my will to his, that I haue no other deſire but to obey
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:178129:81"/> him: When he bids me goe, I goe, when he bids me come, I come, shuning no occaſion by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement to do ſeruice according my power to the sheepe of his folde, with the permiſſion of the Reuerend Paſtours; In this ſort I do viſite the ſick in theſe quarters, I confeſſe thoſe that come to me, being for that purpoſe approued by the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie, <note place="margin">Regulars should haue the approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops.</note> I do adminiſter to them the holy Euchariſt when they come to the Oratorie of this houſe; I goe from village to village teaching the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian doctrine to children, Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the rude, Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelizing the poore, inſtructing the great ones, &amp; making exhortations to them according the tallent which God gaue me. If in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this they do me ſome good, it is according the Apoſtle, to reepe temporall things hauing ſowen ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things; and what I get ouer and aboue what is neceſſarie, I giue it to the poore. Loe how I paſſe ouer this life, caring litle if I be in the ſtate of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:178129:81"/> perfection or no, ſo that I correct my ſelfe of the imperfections which are vnworthie of my eſtate, litle curious of thoſe titles which the Cenobiticall friars do attribute to themſelues, to be the Coadiutours of the Bishops, <note place="margin">Specious titles vvhich the Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars giue to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</note> to be Apoſtolicall men, to leade the Apoſtolicall life, to be men ſent by the ſea Apoſtolike to ſupplie the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the ordinarie Paſtours, to be troupes of ſuccour, to be the props of the Church, to be the pillars and firme colomnes of her which is her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the colome and fundation of truthe, knowing that all theſe qualities are annexed to Prieſthoode, ſith that Prelats ordering Prieſts do call them their cooperators &amp; fellow workers, the ſupporters of their Paſtorall Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and many other very honorable names. The condition of a Monke is truely very venerable, ſo is that of Conuentuall friars, of Religious men; let them call them as they will, and as they pleaſe, or in one word, that of Regulars or of Friars, (albeit the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:178129:82"/> Regular Clerkes do apprehend as much to be called this laſt name, as they would to handle a burning cole without tongs.) But for my part, I beleeue that all men of good vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding will alwaies eſteeme as much <note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of a Prieſt is to be eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as much or more, as any other ſtate in the Church.</note> and more the condition of a Prieſt as any of thoſe. Notwithſtanding to shun the obſtinat contention which the Apoſtle doth ſo expreſly forbid, it is better leaue them in the arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble poſſeſſion of the ſtate of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſeing that by their tongues as by the tongue of Hercules Gaulois the Deſtinies do ſpinne the reputation of men, nothing being well done, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Caſtilian prouerb, but that which proceedeth out of a Monke or friars head.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="151" facs="tcp:178129:82"/>
            <head>THE RESPECT and honour vvhich is due to the Order &amp; dignitie of Prieſthood declared and proued by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie both of holy Scripture and of the ancient Fathers of the Church.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OV haue ſeene gentle Reader in the precedent Diſcours how the Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars to extoll themſelues are not content by their rigorous cenſures to giue a ſentence of exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion againſt Hermites and Secular Prieſts (as they terme them) from the ſtate of perfection in which they pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce the meaneſt of themſelues, in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of their three vowes of pouertie, obedience and chaſtitie, but alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime them to be baſe and of no
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:178129:83"/> conſideration. And that you may iudge whether that be conformable to the holy Scripture &amp; to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the ancient Fathers of the primatiue Church, I thought good to produce here a few authorities of the one &amp; of the other, prouing the dignitie and authoritie of Prieſts.</p>
            <p>God inſtructing the children of Iſraël how to decide all controuerſies that should ariſe amongſt them, ſaid: <hi>Thou shalt come to the Prieſts of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiticall ſtock, and to the iudge, that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.</note> 
               <hi>shall be at that time: and thou shalt aske of them, vvho shall shew thee the truth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The high Prieſts chiefe iudge of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies</note> 
               <hi>of the iudgment. And thou shalt do vvhatſoeuer they, that are preſidentes of the place, vvhich our Lord shall chooſe, shall ſay and teach thee according to his lavv; and thou shalt follovv their ſentence: neither shalt thou decline to the right hand nor to the left hand. But he that shall be proude, refuſing to obey the commandement of the Prieſt, vvhich at that time miniſtreth to our Lord thy God, &amp; the decree of the iudge, that man shall die.</hi>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:178129:83"/> What could be ſaid more to shew the dignitie and authoritie of Prieſts then whoſoeuer would not obey them, nor ſtand to their iudgment should die; but that is not all.</p>
            <p>The Prophet Malachias ſpeaking of the couenant which God made with the tribe of Leui ſaith to the ſame purpoſe: <hi>The lipps of the Prieſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mala.</hi> 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>shall keepe knowledge, and the law they shall require of his mouth: becauſe he is the Angell of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Eccleſiaſticus teaching à man how to carrie himſelf firſt tovvards God, &amp; after towards the Prieſts ſaith <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.</note> thus: <hi>In all thy ſoule feare our Lord, &amp; sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie his Prieſts.</hi> And after; <hi>Honour God withall thy ſoule, &amp; honour the Prieſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saint Peter vvho vvas a Prieſt himſelf ſpeakes thus to Prieſts: <hi>You are an elect generation, a kingly Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>a holy Nation a people of purchaſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was it not to Prieſts that our Sauiour himſelf ſaid: <hi>Whatſoeuer you</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 18.</note> 
               <hi>shall binde vpon earth, shall be bound alſo in heauen: and vvhatſoeuer you shall looſe</hi>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:178129:84"/> 
               <hi>vpon earth, shall be looſed alſo in heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many other paſſages might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced out of holy Scripture to proue the dignitie of Prieſts, &amp; the reſpect which is due to them, but theſe shall fuffice at this time ſo you conſider them well: for you ſee that to Prieſts God gaue power to iudge and decide all controuerſies, and that he gaue ſentence of death vpon any that would not obey them. You ſee more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer that they are called the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells of God, that all men were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to honour and reſpect them, that they are called an elect genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a holy nation, and that their Prieſthood is a Royall dignitie. And which is more then all that, you ſee how CHRIST gaue them the power to looſe and bind vpon earth, and that their act therin is ratified in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            <p>Now reſts to shew what the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers of the primitiue Church do ſay of Prieſthood, and in what
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:178129:84"/> eſteeme Prieſts were in their time, in which there was no ſpeech neither of Benedictins which are the Ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teſt in our Latin Church, and began the yeere 529. nor of Dominicans, nor Franciſcans, which began the yeere 1209. nor yet of Auguſtins, nor Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melites as they are approued by the Church, no nor of Bernardins, much leſſe of the reſt which now, flourish in the Church vnder ſeuerall names, but all was ruled and gouerned by Prieſts.</p>
            <p>Sainct Ignatius Martyr and the third Bishop of Antiochia after S. Peter commaunding all lay perſons to be ſubiect vnto, and reuerence <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Smyrn.</note> Prieſts and Diacons ſaieth thus: <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conos reuereamini vt ex Dei praecepto mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrantes:</hi> Honour yea the Deacons as miniſtring by the precept of God. <note place="margin">Epist. ad Epheſ.</note> And after: <hi>Enitimini chariſsimi ſubiecti eſſe Epiſcopo &amp; Presbyteris &amp; Diaconis. Qui enim his obedit, obedit Christo.</hi> My deareſt doe your beſt to be ſubiect to the Bishop, and Prieſts, and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:178129:85"/> for he that obeyeth theſe obeyeth CHRIST.</p>
            <p>Sainct Policarp diſciple to ſaint Iohn the Apoſtle ſaieth: <hi>Subiectieſtote</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Philip.</note> 
               <hi>Presbyteris, &amp; Diaconis, ſicut Deo, &amp;</hi> CHRISTO. Be yea ſubiect vnto the Prieſts and Deacons, as to God and CHRIST.</p>
            <p>Sainct Clement diſciple to ſaint Peter, ſaith: <hi>Presbyteris ſi aſsiduè in ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſt. Apoſt. l.</hi> 2. c. 8.</note> 
               <hi>docendi verbum Dei laborauerint, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponatur dupla etiam portio in gratiam Apoſtolorum Chriſti, quorum locum te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">c. 35.</note> 
               <hi>tanquam Conſiliarij Epiſcopi &amp; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus Eccleſiae. Si de parentibus ſecundum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">c. 38.</note> 
               <hi>carnem ait diuina Scriptura: Honora pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem &amp; matrem vt benè tibi ſit. Et qui maledicit patri aut matri, morte mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riatur: Quanto magis de Patribus spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualibus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prieſts are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> 
               <hi>verbis Dei moneamur, honore &amp; charitate eos proſequi, vt beneficos &amp; ad Deum Legatos. Quanto anima corpore praeſtantior est, tanto eſt Sacerdotium re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gno excellentius.</hi> Let there be a double portion, reſerued for the Prieſts in honour of the Apoſtles of CHRIST,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:178129:85"/> which shall haue laboured in teaching of the word of God diligently, whoſe places they enioye, as Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours of the Bishop, and the crowne of the Church. They are the Councell &amp; Senat of the Church. If the holy Scripture ſaith of carnall parents: Honour thy Father and thy mother, that it may be well with thee. And whoſoeuer doth curſe his father or his mother, shall die: how much more shall we be admonished by the <note place="margin">Prieſts are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall</note> words of God, of our Spirituall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to reſpect them with honour and charitie, as beneficiall to vs and Legats to God? How much more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the ſoule is then the bodie, ſo much more excellent is Prieſthood before à kingdome. And S. Ignatius <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Smyrn.</note> addeth: <hi>Sacerdotium eſt omnium bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, que in hominibus ſunt apex; qui aduerſus illud furit, non hominem igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minia afficit, ſed Deum &amp; Chriſtum Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum primogenitum, qui naturâ ſolus est ſummus Sacerdos Patris.</hi> Prieſthood is the ornament of all things, vvhich
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:178129:86"/> are in men; whoſoeuer doth rage againſt it, he doth not dishonour a man, but God &amp; Chriſt Ieſus the firſt begotten, who by nature is the only high Prieſt of his Father. The Apoſtles write by ſaint Clements <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> penne: <hi>Si Reges inuadens ſupplicio dignus indicatur, quamuis filius vel amicus ſit, quanto magis. qui Sacerdotibus inſultat: quanto enim Sacerdotium regno eſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentius, cum regendarum animarum officio praeſit, tanto grauiori ſupplicio punitur, qui aduerſus id aliquid temere fecerit, quam qui aduerſus regnum:</hi> If he that ſetteth on a king is iudged worthy of punishement, although he be his ſonne or his frend, how much more should he be blame worthy that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulteth ouer Prieſts. For by how much more Prieſthod excelleth a kingdome, when it doth by office go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne <note place="margin">The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours.</note> ſoules, by ſo much more grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter punishment is he to be afflicted, who shall rashly doe any thing againſt it, then he who hath offended a kingdome.</p>
            <pb n="159" facs="tcp:178129:86"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Presbyteri ſunt</hi> (ſaith ſaint Ignatius) <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Trallen.</note> 
               <hi>conceſſus quidam &amp; coniunctus Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum Chorus, ſine his Eccleſia electa non eſt: nulla ſine his Sanctorum Congregatio, nulla Sanctorum electio. Quid Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium aliud est, quam ſacer caetus, Conſilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rij &amp; aſſeſſores Epiſcopi.</hi> Prieſts are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede a certaine Aſſemblie, and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted quier of the Apoſtles. Without <note place="margin">The Church cannot be vvithout prieſts.</note> theſe the Church is not choſen, without theſe there is no Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Saincts, nor electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Saincts. What elſe is Prieſthood, then an holy Aſſemblie Conſellours and Aſſiſtants of the Bishops?</p>
            <p>Saint Anacletus Pope liuing in this age &amp; made Prieſt by S. Peter, ſaith: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Iniuria Sacerdotum pertinet ad Chriſtum, cuius vice funguntur.</hi> The iniurie done vnto Prieſts, appertaine to Chriſt, whoſe place they ſupplieth.</p>
            <p>Sainct Chryſoſtome treating of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Homil.</hi> 5. <hi>de verb. Iſaiae:</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> the ſame matter and comparing a Prieſt to a king, ſaith: <hi>Ne mihi narres purpuram neque Diadema, neque veſtes aureas, vmbrae ſunt iſthaec omnia, verniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que</hi>
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:178129:87"/> 
               <hi>floſculis leuiora. Ne inquam mihinar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ista, ſed ſi vis videre diſcrimen quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum abſit Rex à Sacerdote, expende mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum poteſtatis vtrique traditae, videbis Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotem multo ſublimius Rege ſedentem. Regius thronus rerum terrenarum admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrationem ſortitus est, nec vltra pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatem hanc praeterea quicquam habet au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatis: Verum Sacerdoti thronus in caelis collocatus est, &amp; de caeleſtibus negotijs pronu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiandi habet authoritatem. Quis haec dicit? ipſe caelorum Rex: Quaecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>que ligaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritis ſuperterra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, erunt ligata &amp; in caelis, &amp; quecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſolueritis ſuper terra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſoluta &amp; in celis. Deus ipſum Regale caput Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotis manibus ſubiecit, nos erudiens, quod hic princeps eſt illo maior.</hi> Speake not to me of theſe things, but if thou wilt ſee the power giuen to them both, thou shalt ſee the Prieſt ſitting much higher in dignitie then the king. The throne of a king is choſen of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of earthlie things: neither hath he any other authoritie beſides this: but to a Prieſt a throne is placed in heauen, &amp; he hath authoritie to
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:178129:87"/> iudge of heauenly buſineſſe. Who ſaieth this? The king of heauen him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Whatſoeuer yee shall bind vpon earth shall be bound alſo in the heauens: and whatſoeuer yee shall looſe on earth, shall be looſed in the heauens. God hath ſubiected to the hands of the Prieſts the Regall head, teaching vs, that this Prince is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then that. The ſame Authour ſpeaking further of this matter ſaith: <hi>Sacerdotibus datum eſt, vt poteſtatem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beant,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſ. l.</hi> 3. <hi>de Sacerd.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quam Deus neque Angelis neque Archangelis datam eſſe voluit. Neque enim ad illos dictum eſt: Quaecunque alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaueritis in terrâ, erunt alligata &amp; in cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, Et quaecunque ſolueritis in terrâ erunt ſoluta &amp; in caelo.</hi> It is giuen to Prieſts, that they shall haue power, which God would haue giuen neither to Angels nor Archangels. For it is not ſaid to them: whatſoeuer you shall bind vpon earth shall be bound alſo in heauen: and whatſoeuer you shall looſe on earth, shall be looſed in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. The power of binding which is
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:178129:88"/> in Princes, is only ouer bodies, that of Prieſts ouer ſoules, and extendeth to heauen.</p>
            <p>A continuation of the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour: <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>Habent &amp; terreſtres Principes vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi poteſtatem verum corporum ſolum: id autem quod dico Sacerdotum vinculum ipſam etiam animam contingit atque ad caelos vſque peruadit.</hi> Terrene Princes alſo haue the power of fetters, but of the body only; but that which I ſay, the bonds of Prieſts toucheth the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le it ſelf, and paſſeth vnto the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. This is the doctrine deliuered by CHRIST, ſo expounded both by the Greeke and Latine Church.</p>
            <p>Item, In an other place he ſaith: <hi>An</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſt. Homil.</hi> 2. <hi>ſuper</hi> 2. <hi>ad Timot.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ignoras quid ſit Sacerdos? Angelus vtique Domini est, non ex ſe ipſo loquitur, ſi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicis, non illum deſpicis ſed Deum qui illu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ordinauit.</hi> Art thou ignorant what is a Prieſt? he is verily the Angell of our Lord, he doth not ſpeake of himſelf, if you deſpiſe, it is not him that you deſpiſe, but God who ordayned him.</p>
            <p>And in an other place: <hi>Monachorum</hi>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:178129:88"/> 
               <hi>certamen ingens &amp; labor multus eſt: Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſi conferre quis volet inſtituti illius ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dores</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chryſ. lib. de Sacerd.</note> 
               <hi>cum rectè adminiſtrato Sacerdotio, certè tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe inter duo illa diſcrimen com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periet, quantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt inter priuatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Regem.</hi> The conflict and labour of Monks is great: but if any would confer the pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; labour of that inſtitution with prieſthood duely adminiſtred; truely he shall find as much difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene them both as betwene a king and a priuat man. Loe how farr he putts à Prieſt beyond a Monke or Religious man.</p>
            <p>Saint Hierome who was himſelf a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Hier. in Malac.</hi> 3.</note> Religious man ſaith: <hi>Sacerdotibus ac Leuitis honorem debitum deferamus: quod qui non fecerit, Deum fraudare &amp; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantare conuincitur.</hi> Let vs giue due honour to Prieſts &amp; Leuites: which, who will not do is manifeſtly proued to defraude and ſupplant God.</p>
            <p>The ſame Authour in an other place <note place="margin">Epiſt, ad Heliod.</note> ſaith: <hi>Mihi ante Presbyterum ſedere non licet, illi ſi peccauero licet tradere me Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thane in interitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> carnis.</hi> It is not lawfull
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:178129:89"/> for me to ſitt before the Prieſt, for him it is lawfall if I ſinne, to deliuer me vp to Sathan, to the deſtruction of the flesh.</p>
            <p>Saint Ambroſe in his learned trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the dignitie of Prieſts ſalutes <note place="margin">Lib. de dig. Sacer.</note> them with thoſe venerable Epitets: <hi>Audite me, beatiſsimi Patres, etſi dignum ducitis, ſanctiſsimi Fratres, audite me ſtirps Leuitica, germen Sacerdotale, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pago ſanctificata, Duces &amp; Rectores gregis Chriſti.</hi> Et paulò poſt. <hi>Honor &amp; ſublimitas Sacerdotalis, nullis poterit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parationibus adaequari, ſi Regum fulgori compares, &amp; Principum diademati, longe erit inferius, quam ſi plumbi metallu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, auri fulgorem co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pares: quippè cum videas Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum &amp; Principum colla ſubmitti genibus Sacerdotum, &amp; exoſculatis eorum dextris orationibus eorum credunt ſe communiri.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heare me, moſt bleſſed Fathers, &amp; if you take it in good part, moſt holy <note place="margin">It is due to Prieſts to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> Brothers, heare me you Leuiticall ſtock, you Sacerdotall branch, you ſanctified race, you leaders and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of Chriſts flock. <hi>And a litle</hi>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:178129:89"/> 
               <hi>after;</hi> The honour and ſublimitie of prieſthood cannot be equalized by any compariſons, if you compare it to the ſplendor of kings, &amp; to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces crownes, that will be farr more vnequall to it, then if you did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the mettall of lead to the ſplendor of gold: for you ſee the neckes of kings and Princes bowed downe to the knees of Prieſts, and hauing kiſſed their right hands they beleeue that they are fortified and ſtrengthned by their prayers.</p>
            <p>S. Chryſoſtome wrote ſix bookes of the dignitie and power of Prieſts putting it aboue all kings, Princes &amp; Potentats of the earth, and in his third booke he ſaith thus: <hi>Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium ipſum in terra quidem peragitur, ſed in rerum caeleſtium claſſem, ordinem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que referendum eſt, atque id quidem me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rito; quippe non mortalis quiſpiam, non Angelus, non alia quaeuis creata potentia, ſed Deus ipſe ordinem huiuſmodi diſponit.</hi> Prieſhood truely is exerciſed in earth, but it is to be referred to the
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:178129:90"/> ranke and order of celeſtiall things, and that truely very worthely; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is no mortall man, nor An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell nor any other created power, but God himſef that doth diſpoſe &amp; appoint this order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sacerdotibus ſicut Epiſcopis,</hi> inquit ſanctus Iſidorus, <hi>dispenſatio Myſterio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Dei commiſſa eſt: praeſunt enim</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Diu. Off. cap.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>Eccleſiae, &amp; in confectione diuina cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris &amp; ſanguinis conſortes cum Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copo ſunt, ſimiliter in doctrina populorum &amp; in officio predicationis.</hi> To Prieſts as to Bishops the diſpenſation of the myſteries of God is committed: for that they beare the rule in the Church and in the diuine conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the body and bloud of Chriſt, they are conſorts with the Bishops likewiſe in teaching the people, and in the office of preaching.</p>
            <p>Philippus de Hareing a Religious and a moſt learned Abbot in his worke which he wrote foure hundred and fiftie yeeres agoe: <hi>De dignitate, ſcientia &amp; iuſtitia &amp; continentia Cleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum,</hi>
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:178129:90"/> doth highly commend the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulars, but in euery chapter he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth the Clergie before all Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, though himſelf was one: In his 17. chapter he ſaith thus: <hi>Noſtrum eſt nouiſsimum locum eligere nec ad altiora volatu praeſumptuoſo nos ipſos erigere.</hi> It is our partes (that is to ſay, the part of Religious men) to chooſe the laſt place, and not by a preſumptuous flight to eleuat our ſelues to higher things. And in his 17. epiſtle he ſaieth, that from all the bounds and limits of the earth, all antiquitie did euer extoll the Clericall order, and euer gaue it amongſt the other Orders the principall ranke and degree, and though by diuine diſpoſition a Soil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour or Ruſtique do excell in ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, yet the Clergie man in excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of Eccleſiaſticall dignitie; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Clergie man, as we do ſometimes, decline to worldly things, and to the weake &amp; poore elements, yet their Order declineth not in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie. Thus he: To which I muſt
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:178129:91"/> add this other paſſage of ſaint Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me which doth occur vnto me: <hi>Communi Presbyterorum Concilio Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae</hi> 
               <note place="margin">S. Hier in ep. ad Tit.</note> 
               <hi>gubernabantur:</hi> The Churches were gouerned by the common councell of Prieſts; And I muſt not forget this paſſage of Bellarmin who was a Ieſuit and a Cardinall: <hi>Tria ſunt Eccleſiae membra praecipua, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum eorum est, qui in ſtatu perfectionis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Belar. l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>de Gemitu Columbae.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>adeptae eſſe dicuntur, qui ſunt Epiſcopi Eccleſiarum Principes, &amp; Magiſtri, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus adiungimus Presbyteros qui ſunt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nores Sacerdotes, atque eorum adminiſtros.</hi> There are three chiefe members of the church; the firſt of them are thoſe that are ſaid to be in the ſtate of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection acquired, which are the Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops the Princes and maiſters of the churches, to which we ioyne the Prieſts, who are the inferior Prieſts, and their aſſiſtants. And the ſame Authour in the preface of his ſecond booke, <hi>De Monachis</hi> ſaith: <hi>Diſſeruimus, libro ſuperiori de Epiſcopis &amp; Clericis, id eſt, de prima &amp; nobiliſsima parte corporis</hi>
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:178129:91"/> 
               <hi>Ecleſiaſtici:</hi> We haue diſcourſed in the former booke of Bishops and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie-men that is to ſay, of the chiefe &amp; nobleſt part of the Eccleſiaſticall body.</p>
            <p>The Councell of Trent ſpeaking of the Hierarchie of the Church ſaith thus: <hi>Si quis dixerit in Eccleſia Catholica</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>non eſſe Hierarchiam Diuina ordinatione inſtitutam que conſtat ex Epiſcopis, Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteris &amp; miniſtris anathemaſit.</hi> Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer will ſay that in the Catholike Church there is not a Hierarchie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by diuine ordinance, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth of Bishops, Prieſts &amp; Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, let him be curſed. Loe, You ſee that the Councell makes no mention here of Regulars, which by all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihoode it would haue done, if they had bene of this Hierarchie.</p>
            <p>To be briefe in all theſe paſſages, both out of Scripture &amp; out of the Fathers which are not the tieth of the paſſages which might be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for this matter, the Reader will ſee but litle or no mention of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulars;
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:178129:92"/> and in the litle mention that is made of them by late writers, he shall find that Prieſts, both for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnitie &amp; office are ſtill preferred to them, and are put in a farr higher ranke then they; which conſidered, he may conclude with him ſelf that the propoſitions ſpecified in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatorie Epiſtle of this Tretiſe, are of a new ſtamp forged by the Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars themſelues: For had there bene any ſuch prerogatiue graunted to them by God or by his Church, who can imagine that all ancient writers, ſpeaking of all the members &amp; digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Church would omitt to ſpeake of them, &amp; of theſe preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues which now they challenge to themſelues? Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding I do not wish Prieſts (but counſell the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie) to take any pride of this, nor ſett the leſſe by Regulars, but acknowledge them to be a noble &amp; profitable portion of Gods Church, and as ſuch to embrace &amp; cherish them; and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther receiue iniuries patiently of
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:178129:92"/> them, then offer them any, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that ſaying of the Apoſtle: <hi>If you bite and eate one an other: take</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 15</note> 
               <hi>heede you be not conſumed one of an other.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
